<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Forms of prayer for every day in the week, morning and evening composed for the use of private families / by John Meriton ...</title>
            <author>Meriton, John, 1636-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 106 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9947</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12926854</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12926854</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95531</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50680)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95531)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 989:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Forms of prayer for every day in the week, morning and evening composed for the use of private families / by John Meriton ...</title>
                  <author>Meriton, John, 1636-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 199 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.H. for Robert Boulter ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95531:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FORMS OF PRAYER FOR EVERY <hi rend="blackletterType">Day in the Week,</hi> MORNING and EVENING. Compoſed for the uſe of <hi>PRIVATE FAMILIES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Meriton</hi> D. D. Rector of St. <hi>Michael Cornhill London,</hi> and Lecturer at St. <hi>Martins</hi> in the Fields.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. H.</hi> for <hi>Robert Boulter,</hi> at the <hi>Turks Head</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95531:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95531:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:95531:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95531:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THat all Men are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to worſhip God by praiſing and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, is ſo evident by the light of natural Reaſon, as well as the Revelation of Scripture, that none can queſtion it, but they whoſe Immoralities and improved Debaucheries, have laid ſuch a foundation of
<pb facs="tcp:95531:4"/>Atheiſm as makes them incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to deny the Being of God, and loath to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their dependance upon him, leſt this ſhould involve them in the dreadful conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of their being account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to him. And that men ought dayly to pay this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and Tribute of Praiſe and Prayer unto God, as they ſtand linked in the relations of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, though all readily grant, that are ſenſible of the Sins there committed that need his Pardon, of the many Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Spiritual bleſſings either wanted and to be ſought at<pb facs="tcp:95531:4"/>his Hands, or injoyed, and to be thankfully acknowledged, yet the too common neglect of Family Prayer is (it's to be feared, and he muſt have a very eaſie and credulous charity that can be otherwiſe minded) not only one of the many inſtances of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Piety and Religion, but one of the provoking Sins that cry aloud, to Heaven for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. It is no doubt by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny totally omitted from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible ſtupidity, &amp; an irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, profane diſregard of God and their Duty; but by others not a few (as was well and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably<pb facs="tcp:95531:5"/>ſuggeſted by the Good Man that earneſtly preſſed me to this undertaking) only from a conſciouſneſs of their inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility decently to perform it. Now that this might be neither a feigned pretence nor a real hinderance: But that they that like <hi>Joſhua</hi> are willing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſerve God with their Families, might have Materials of Devotion ready at hand; As the Water near the Road, offered it ſelf to the Eunuch willing to be Baptized, I have for the help of ſuch as can read, complyed with my Friends deſire, and compoſed<pb facs="tcp:95531:5"/>a Form of Weekly Prayers, Morning and Evening. And though their length will not, I hope, be complained of by any whoſe leaſure may allow, and whoſe Affections can vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly attend one quarter of an hours ſolemn and religious Addreſs to God: Yet in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of others multiplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Buſineſs, and that flatting and depreſſion of Spirits that may follow from it; all the Prayers are printed in many diſtinct Paragraphs, that ſome of the Confeſſions or Petitions or both may eaſily, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſturbing their Devotion,<pb facs="tcp:95531:6"/>be paſs'd over and the Prayer thereby ſo contracted as to ſuit their convenience: And I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire they would rather do ſo than wholly omit the Duty, for better a ſhort Prayer than none at all.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95531:6"/>
            <head>Lord's Day Morning.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmighty, moſt high and holy, Lord God, who art the glorious Creator, Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all things in Heaven and in Earth, and moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be praiſed, and honoured by all Creatures; And with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite kindneſs and compaſſion haſt redeemed loſt, and undone Sinners, by thine only beloved
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. ult.</note> Son, whom thou haſt deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to death for their offences, and raiſed again for their juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and ſo thou art for<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95531:7"/>ever to be loved, and delighted in, obeyed, and worſhipped, praiſed and honoured by thy redeemed ones. We thy poor Creatures and Children are here before thee this Morning, humbly ſenſible of this our great and bounden duty, and of our own inability, without the aſſiſtance of thy Grace to perform it. And in a deep ſenſe both of our duty and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency, we deſire to offer up our ſacrifice of praiſe and thankſgiving to thy Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, our mighty Creator, and moſt merciful Redeemer, and humbly deſire that thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſanctifie and prepare both our Souls and Bodies by the Grace of thy Holy Spirit, that we may preſent unto thee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable thank-offerings.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95531:7"/>We acknowledge, O Lord, that beſides the ſins of our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings &amp; common Imployments, and even thoſe of the Week laſt paſt, whereby we have greatly offended thee, the ſins of our holy duties, and our profanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this thy holy day, have given thee a juſt provocation to withdraw the grace of thy good Spirit from us, and leave us to the ignorance and vanity of our own minds, the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings and diſtractions of our thoughts, the earthlineſs and ſenſuality of our affections, the hardneſs, impenitency and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief of our hearts: And then by all the duties of thy Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service we ſhould diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thee, and by offering the Sacrifices of Fools, increaſe our own guilt before thee.<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95531:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95531:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95531:9"/>But we humbly beſeech thee, moſt merciful Father, forgive us all our paſt offences, that they may not ſtand as a partition Wall between thy Majeſty and us to hinder either thy Grace from coming down upon us as Rain upon the tender Herb, or our Prayers from coming up before thee as Incenſe.</p>
            <p>Fill every one of our hearts with awful thoughts of thee, as a God that ſearcheſt hearts, and art throughly acquainted with our moſt ſecret imaginations, diſpoſitions and purpoſes; and becauſe thou art a God of purer Eyes than to behold iniquity, Let us worſhip thee with an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhip; ſo as to fear thy Goodneſs, and love thy Juſtice, to delight in thy Mercy, truſt and rely upon thy Power and<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95531:9"/>Faithfulneſs, to admire, praiſe and imitate thy Holineſs.</p>
            <p>In the publick Duties and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of this thy Day, help us ſo to joyn with the Aſſembly of thy Servants, that our hearts may be inflamed with a love of thee, and delight in thee, and in the vigour and fervency of devout affections, we may to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether glorifie thy holy and great Name, ſet forward our own edification, and comfort, and advance in thoſe ways of holineſs that lead to everlaſting happineſs: And ſeeing in great mercy and compaſſion to our Souls thou art pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to us thy Sabbaths, and the uſe of thine ordinances, which by our many and great ſins we have long ſince forfeited, Let us not, like Children ſitting in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95531:10"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 16.</note> the Market-place, trifle away the precious opportunities and means of Grace and Salvation.</p>
            <p>Help us ſeriouſly to conſider, when we are in thine Houſe, the Habitation of thine Holineſs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26. 8.</note> and the place where thine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour dwelleth, the glorious Majeſty, and ſpotleſs perfect pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of that God with whom we have to do, and let us behave our ſelves in thy ſacred and dreadful preſence, with that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and holy fear, that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and lowlineſs of mind, that ſimplicity, and godly ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that heavenly mindedneſs, and purity of affection, that firm conſtancy of reſolution to devote our ſelves to thee, by our hearty obedience to thy Laws, as it becomes duſt and aſhes, vile Creatures that dwell
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95531:10"/>in houſes of Clay, when they worſhip and do homage to that Sovereign Majeſty, the Throne of whoſe Glory is in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt heavens.</p>
            <p>Let us hear thy holy Word, that ſhall be read and preached to us, as the Oracles of God, and thoſe Divine Meſſages which thou haſt ſent us from Heaven to guide us in the ways that lead thither. Let us heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to it with diligent attention, imbrace it with holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly affections, rejoycing in the Promiſes, dreading the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, loving and practiſing the commands of it, let us receive it with meekneſs and mix it with
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 21.</note> Faith, that it may be an ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 2.</note> word to the ſalvation of our Souls. And as the Rain
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 10, 11.</note> cometh down, &amp; the Snow from<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95531:11"/>Heaven, and returneth not thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but watereth the Earth, and maketh it bring forth Fruit, and bud, that it may give ſeed to the Sower, and bread to the eater; So let not thy Word, that goeth forth out of thy mouth, return to thee void, but accompliſh that which thou pleaſeſt, and proſper in the thing whereto thou haſt ſent it.</p>
            <p>Help us to pray in faith and fervency, let all our petitions be addreſſed to the Throne of thy Grace, in the prevailing name of thy dear Son, and by the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of thy holy Spirit, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Supplication: And that the Prayers that we ſhall this day ſend up to Heaven may find a gracious acceptance with thee, Let the holy Ghoſt make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26.</note> in our hearts, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95531:11"/>holy, humble, earneſt and hearty deſires, and let our bleſſed Redeemer make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion in Heaven, and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en all the diſpleaſing unſavori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Fleſh, with the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. 3.</note> of his Incenſe.</p>
            <p>Let us give thanks unto thee with our whole hearts, and let all that is within us magnifie and praiſe thy Name, as for all thy mercies to our Souls and Bodies, for this Life and a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo eſpecially for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, by the precious death and Sufferings of thy Son, and finiſhing that glorious work, by the raiſing him from the Dead. Raiſe up our Souls, O Lord, to the higheſt pitch of hearty thankfulneſs in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance and ſenſe of thoſe ineſtimable benefits, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95531:12"/>to us and thy whole Church from this great and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient Redeemer. And help us ſo to ſing praiſes to thee and to the Lamb that ſits with thee up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy Throne, that by praiſing thee on Earth, we may tune and prepare our hearts for thoſe glorious and triumphant Praiſes, that in Heaven will be the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and happineſs of thy Saints, to all Eternity.</p>
            <p>Let us ſo carry our ſelves this whole day, as remembring thou haſt ſeparated and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied it to thine own ſervice, and made Religion, which is the great Work of every day, the more proper and peculiar im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of this.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt the thoughts, the words, the practiſes of other<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95531:12"/>days, and this which thou haſt ſet apart to different purpoſes, and ſo ſanctifie this day of holy Reſt, and make it our delight, that we may be ſanctified and fitted for that perpetual Reſt that remains for thy People, and ſatisfied with thoſe Rivers of
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 16. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> Pleaſures, that are at thy Right Hand for evermore.</p>
            <p>Bleſs, we beſeech thee, thy whole Church, and that part of it eſpecially which thou haſt planted in theſe Kingdoms. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don our many Sins, and remove far away from us whatever may provoke thy diſpleaſure, unſettle our foundations or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb our peace. Let thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, our Sovereign Lord the King, find favour in thine Eyes, So bleſs Him in His Perſon, in His Counſels and Enterprizes,<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95531:13"/>that upon his Head His Crown may long flouriſh, and His Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be a publick Bleſſing to theſe Kingdoms. Govern thoſe that govern under Him in Church and State, and let all His Subjects in their ſeveral Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Stations, do what lies in them, to the healing of our wide Breaches, the reſtoring of Chriſtian Love and Charity, the eſtabliſhment of Truth and

<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 3.</note> Righteouſneſs, and keeping the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace.</p>
            <p>Let all afflicted ones in what kind ſoever, find thy gracious hand ready for their relief and ſuccour, and by the more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate working of thy holy Spirit, ſupply the want of thy publick ordinances to all that deſire them, and are by Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment,<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95531:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Baniſhment, Sickneſs or any other hinderance deprived of them, &amp; let us that by thy ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial favour, are bleſſed with the rich and in eſtimable priviledge injoying them, carefully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them to a growth in Grace, and the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, to an increaſe of Faith and all godlineſs, till we come to the full and perfect happineſs of an immediate injoying thee without them in thy heavenly and everlaſting Kingdom, by thy dear Son Jeſus Chriſt our ever bleſſed Redeemer, through whoſe Merit and Mediation, and in whoſe Form of Words, we are bold to call thee Father, ſaying,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:95531:14"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95531:14"/>
            <head>Lord's Day Evening.</head>
            <p>EVer bleſſed, and gracious Lord God, and in Jeſus Chriſt our loving and merciful Father, and moſt liberal and open-handed Benefactor, from whoſe favour, and kindneſs, we have all the good things that we receive in this Life, and the hopes of a better to make us everlaſtingly happy in the next. We thy poor Servants acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging our manifold unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the leaſt of thy mercies, and the guilt of thoſe ſins, whereby we have made fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent forfeitures of them, are here before thee, to offer up to thee our Evening Sacrifice of hearty praiſe and thanſgivings
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95531:15"/>for all thoſe bleſſings that with a moſt free and unwearied bounty thou haſt been pleaſed to confer upon us, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to us.</p>
            <p>Thy hand hath formed us in the Womb, given us Life, and Breath, and Being, and having brought us into the World, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on us many convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Life, that have made our Being in the World eaſie and delightful to us: Thine, O Lord, is our health and ſtrength, our eaſe and liberty; thine the Air we breath in, and the Earth we tread upon, thine our Food and our Raiment, the Sun that ſhines to give us Light, and the Rain that falls to give us plenty, thine the uſe of our Limbs, and thine the exerciſe of our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Reaſon. And we<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95531:15"/>bleſs thy Name for all thoſe outward and temporal bleſſings, the multitude whereof, (ſuch is thy goodneſs) makes us unable to recount them, and whoſe dayly repetition, that ſhould heighten our eſteem of them, and thankfulneſs for them, makes us (ſuch is our folly and weakneſs) too apt to underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue them.</p>
            <p>But above all we adore, and with our higheſt and heartieſt praiſes, deſire to magnifie thy rich and free Grace for ſpiritual bleſſings in heavenly things in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, that tend to the renewing us after thy likeneſs in this life, and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying of us with it in the life to come.</p>
            <p>We bleſs thee for that ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable gift, the Foundation of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95531:16"/>all others, the Son of thy dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt love, and everlaſting delight, whom in a tender compaſſion to our Souls, thou haſt ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world to be our Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Saviour, that when we had by our ſins ruined and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done our ſelves, and were ſo lyable to thy ſevere diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and inſupportable venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that no creature in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or Earth could deliver us from it, it pleaſed thee in thine infinite goodneſs, to find out, and in thy mercy to afford us in him an admirable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought of way of recovery. Now, O Lord, we know thou loveſt us, and haſt a favour and good will towards us, ſeeing thou haſt not withheld thy Son, thine only Son from us.</p>
            <p>Ever bleſſed be thy Name,<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95531:16"/>that thy Son, who is God over all, bleſſed for ever, took upon him our humane Fleſh; that while he lived here upon Earth, he inſtructed us, both by his heavenly doctrine and exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry life, that he gave himſelf to Death as the price of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, that he compleated that great work, in his power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and glorious Reſurrection, wherein he conquered and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed over all the powers of darkneſs, and hath begotten us again to a lively hope of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance incorruptible, unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3, 4.</note> that fadeth not away, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in Heaven for us. We praiſe thee, that, when he had wrought a perfect Righteouſneſs for us upon Earth, he aſcended up to Heaven, &amp; ſits at thy right hand to repreſent and plead it<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95531:17"/>on our behalf, by his prevailing interceſſion; that when he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up on high, he led cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive thoſe ſpiritual enemies that held us in captivity, and for the
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11.</note> edification of his Church gave gifts unto Men, Apoſtles and Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtors and Teachers. That thou haſt
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 10</note> given thy holy Word to be a Lamp to our Feet, and a Light to our Paths, and when many Nations ſit in Darkneſs and the Regions of the Shadow of
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 78, 79.</note> Death, the day ſpring from on high hath viſited us, to guide our Feet into the way of Peace. We give thee our humble and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thanks, that thou ſtill keepeſt open the doors of thy Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that for our unfruitfulneſs thou mighteſt have ſhut and barred againſt us, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95531:17"/>our vile unworthineſs, thou graciouſly admitteſt us to Communion with thy Self in thy publick Ordinances, the Reading and Preaching of thy Word; Prayers to and Praiſes of thy Name, and the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of thy holy Sacraments, wherein thou doſt lively repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Death of thy Son, and to all worthy Receivers doſt firmly aſſure and convey the precious benefits of it, and bind them to walk anſwerably to them.</p>
            <p>And we further thank thee with enlarged hearts, O our heavenly Father, for all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of thy Covenant, which thou haſt ſealed with the Blood of thy Son; and given unto us that we might by them be the more encouraged in an holy<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95531:18"/>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1.</note> obedience, cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the Fleſh and Spirit, and perfecting holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4.</note> in thy fear, be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Divine Nature.</p>
            <p>We can never enough mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie thy mercy and goodneſs that thou haſt made our duty to be a part of our happineſs, and that it is not only neceſſary but beſt for us to love and fear, truſt and ſerve, obey and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thee, and that we are not only bound to be ſober and temperate, meek and patient, juſt and charitable, but much better by being ſo.</p>
            <p>And what thanks can we ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to thee, who in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our weakneſs and ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhneſs to the performance of our duty, haſt not only ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us the lively and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95531:18"/>examples of thy Saints and Martyrs, but aſſiſted and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled us by the grace of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, that our ſufficiency
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5.</note> hath been of thee, who of our ſelves have not been ſufficient to think a good thought, and for the Reward of thoſe Graces and Duties that are the Fruits of thy Spirit working in us, haſt promiſed ſuch a glory and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in the world to come, as ſurpaſſes not our deſires only, but our thoughts and concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</p>
            <p>We further glorifie thy great Name, O Lord, that thy rich and free Grace hath been the only motive to the beſtowing all thy Mercies upon us, guilty and wretched ſinners, that our unworthineſs hath not hindred the ſtreaming forth of thy<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95531:19"/>goodneſs, but thy goodneſs hath born away before it all conſideration of our unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; And O how admirable in themſelves, and how obliging to us are all thoſe favours and kindneſſes, which not only without our merits, but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding our deſerts of wrath and vengeance, thou haſt conferred upon us, bold and provoking Rebels!</p>
            <p>We are, O Lord, as thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, infinitely below thee, but as Sinners we have fooliſhly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and ſet our ſelves againſt thee; we have broken thy holy Laws, abuſed thine abundant Mercies, ſlighted the tenders of thy Grace, diſhonoured and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified afreſh our great and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Redeemer, reſiſted and grieved thy holy Spirit, profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95531:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>and polluted thy Sabbaths and Ordinances, that are both the Pledges and means of thy Grace and Favour. And were there no other Sin upon our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but of theſe thy days and the holy duties of them, they might for ever fill our Faces with ſhame, and lay us under thy wrathful diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>We have come unprepared to thy ſolemn worſhip, and with unhallowed hearts entred the Sanctuary and approached the preſence of the moſt holy God, we have been heedleſs and unattentive hearers of thy holy Word, remembring little of what we have heard, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting leſs of what we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred; we have been flat, and unaffected in offering up thy praiſe, and our hearts have<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95531:20"/>been earthly, dull and diſtracted in our Prayers, how often have we turned our Backs upon thy holy Table judging, our ſelves unworthy of the precious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits that are there tendered; or if we have not altogether neglected the ſacred Ordinance, we have not, as we might have done, grown in the graces and the comforts of thy holy Spirit by it.</p>
            <p>How ſeldom have we been ſeriouſly exerciſed in Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and either ſo recollected thy Mercies, as to become ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of our obligation by them, or ſo thought on our ways, as
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 59
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to turn our feet unto thy Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
            <p>Forgive us, O Lord, we pray thee all our paſt offences, and as the beſt aſſurance of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs,<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95531:20"/>let us not ſo offend any more. Graciouſly guide us into the ways of truth and holineſs, and that we may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways fear thee, let us ſet our ſelves continually in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and ſo obſerve and ſtand in aw of thine all-ſeeing Eye, that all our evil thoughts, words and actions may be ſcattered by it.</p>
            <p>Let us dye with Chriſt in the crucifying of our Fleſh, with its affections and luſts, and riſe with him to a life of holy and new obedience; that as Chriſt being raiſed from the dead
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 9.</note> dieth no more, ſo being riſen with him, we may wilfully ſin no more, but run the race of thy Commandments, till at length we receive the prize of a glorious and incorruptible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:95531:21"/>Extend thy mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to all the Sons of Men, and let the Kingdoms of the World, that are ignorant of thee and thy Salvation, behold the light of thy glorious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and become obedient to the Scepter of thy Son.</p>
            <p>Bleſs thy whole Church, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Miſts of Ignorance and Errour, heal the breaches of Schiſm and Diviſion, quench the Wildfire of Strife and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; cleanſe the Spots of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs, and Superſtition that defile and deform it; and make thy Sion the Beauty and the joy of the whole Earth.</p>
            <p>Be gracious to theſe ſinful Nations, forgive thoſe many and great ſins, that have pulled down thy heavy Judgments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and ſtill provoke thee<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95531:21"/>more and more to puniſh us, and particularly pardon, we pray thee, our wicked and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous profanation of this thy day, our unthankfulneſs for the light of thy bleſſed Goſpel, and walking unſuitably to the principles of that holy Religion that hath been of a long time publickly taught and profeſſed among us. Waſh us through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 2.</note> from our Iniquities, and cleanſe us from our Sins, and grant that by unity, and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and holineſs of life, we may glorifie thy great Name, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the truth of our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and adorn the Goſpel of God our Saviour. Continue thy Goſpel among us, defeat and overthrow the evil deſigns of bloody and deceitful Men that would pervert the truth of<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95531:22"/>it, by mixtures of Superſtition and Idolatry; and let all that
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 16.</note> love thy Salvation, ſay continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, let the Lord be magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <p>Guide and guard, bleſs and protect thine Anointed Servant our Soveraign Lord, King <hi>Charles;</hi> let his days be many, his Counſels wiſe and religious, his enterprizes ſucceſsful, his Reign happy to himſelf and all his Subjects: Cloath his Enemies with ſhame, and upon his head
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132. 18.</note> let his Crown flouriſh, let the Biſhops and Paſtors of thy Church further the edification of it, by ſoundneſs of Doctrine, and holineſs of Life; and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates cheriſh, and defend it by the encouragement of all virtue and goodneſs, and the puniſhment and ſuppreſſion of<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95531:22"/>all vice and ungodlineſs; and let all men follow after peace and holineſs, without which
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 14.</note> none ſhall ſee the Lord.</p>
            <p>Refreſh and ſupport the Sons and Daughters of Sorrow, and in the multitude of their
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. 19.</note> thoughts within them, let thy comforts delight their Souls.</p>
            <p>Be gracious and favourable to us that are here before thee, forgive us all our Sins and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not againſt us thoſe iniquities that have this day polluted our holy offerings; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and protect us this night, from all thoſe dangers and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs that might overtake us, and let us find ſafety under the ſhadow of thy wings; refreſh our frail Bodies with a quiet and moderate reſt, and help us in the renewed ſtrength of it,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95531:23"/>vigorouſly to ſerve thee in a faithful diſcharge of the duties of the next day; and all our days let us live to thee, that in the end of them we may live with thee, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, who hath taught and commanded us when we Pray, to ſay;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:95531:23"/>
            <head>Monday Morning.</head>
            <p>O Moſt mighty, Lord God, and merciful Father, the Author of our Being, both Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Souls, and the Giver of every good Gift, that may tend to the benefit and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of both our Souls and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, we thy poor and moſt, unworthy Servants are here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee this Morning, thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to acknowledge thy great goodneſs, in all the bleſſings we injoy, for this Life and a better, humbly to implore thy mercy in the free pardon of all our Sins, and earneſtly to beg the grace of thy holy Spirit, that we may faithfully diſcharge the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of pardoned Sinners, and<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95531:24"/>anſwer the Obligations thou haſt laid upon us by thy mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold bleſſings.</p>
            <p>We bleſs thy holy and great Name, as for all Spiritual and Temporal bleſſings beſtowed on us through thy Son, ſo particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly for all the ordinances of the Goſpel and the priviledges of thy Houſe yeſterday injoyed, and for the ſafety and quiet reſt, and refreſhment of the laſt
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 22.</note> night; acknowledging it to be of thy mercies that we are not conſumed, and becauſe thy compaſſions fail not, for hadſt thou rewarded us after our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, we had long ſince been incapable of any the leaſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and had been puniſhed with utmoſt and everlaſting mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            <p>We confeſs, O Lord, there<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95531:24"/>hath on thy part been nothing wanting that might work in us a Conformity to thy Will, but there hath wanted on ours, a care to pleaſe thee and a fear to offend thee, a love and delight in thee, and a ſtedfaſt purpoſe to give up our ſelves to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of thy heavenly Laws: And which hath made us more remiſs and negligent, we have not firmly believed the excellent and glorious things thou haſt promiſed upon a compliance with thy Will, nor the fearful and inſupportable puniſhments, which thou haſt threatned to our diſobedience. We have with great folly over deſired, over loved, over truſted to, and over delighted in the things of this World, which cannot profit us, nor in the leaſt promote our<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95531:25"/>ſpiritual intereſt, or eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, whileſt we have been
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 33.</note> careleſs and negligent in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy Kingdom and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, though for our incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to do that in the firſt place, thou haſt graciouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that all the conveniencies of life ſhall be added unto us. How have vain tranſitory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and pleaſures drawn off our hearts from the love of thee, who alone canſt make us happy, and from a delight in thy Laws, in the keeping of which there
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 11.</note> is great reward? We have with too great care pampered our vile bodies and made proviſion
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 14.</note> for our fleſh, to fulfil the luſts of it, and with too little provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for our Souls, and ſecured their happineſs in the future ſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:95531:25"/>We have miſimployed the Talents intruſted with us, in the ſervice of Sin, and abuſed to thy diſhonour, our time, and opportunity of doing good; our health and ſtrength, our eaſe, and liberty, our credit and plenty, the members of our Bodies, the faculties of our Souls, which being received from thy bounty, ſhould all have been improved to thy glory; nor have we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the great day of reckoning, wherein we muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our Stewardſhip, and
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 2.</note> be no longer Stewards.</p>
            <p>We acknowledge, O Lord, that we are guilty Sinners, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to help our ſelves, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy that thou ſhouldſt help us; our own conſciences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us, and thou mighteſt<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95531:26"/>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>John.</hi> 3. 20</note> much more condemn us, for thou knoweſt more by us than we do by our ſelves, and art greater than our conſciences.</p>
            <p>But, O God, be merciful to us, and ſpare us, in the multitude of thy tender compaſſions: Thou that haſt promiſed pardon and forgiveneſs to all repenting Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, work in us, we beſeech thee, a ſerious and unfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and let us thereby obtain remiſſion of Sins: And by a true and lively faith in our Lord
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 24, 25.</note> Jeſus Chriſt, whom thou haſt ſet ſorth to be a propitiation, through faith in his blood, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us freely by thy Grace, and let not any of our ſins be charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon us to our condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But let us by his Merits and Righteouſneſs be ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the guilt of them,<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95531:26"/>that we may ſerve thee in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 75.</note> and holineſs before thee, all the days of our life: And grant that as Chriſt dyed for us, that were dead in ſin, and under a ſentence of death for it, we may not henceforth live unto our ſelves, but unto him which
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 15.</note> dyed for us and roſe again.</p>
            <p>Guide our Feet into thoſe ways of righteouſneſs and peace, temperance and ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, mercy, meekneſs and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that are well-pleaſing to thee, and guard us againſt the temptations of the World, the Devil and our own naughty Hearts, that we never depart from them. Let a continued ſenſe of thine Omnipreſence and all-ſeeing Eye, make us upright and ſincere, in the diſcharge of every duty; careful and vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95531:27"/>for the avoiding of every ſin, firm and conſtant in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting every temptation; let us ſo ſet thee alway before us, that thou being at our right hand,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 8.</note> we may not be moved.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 9.</note> Keep us ſtedfaſt in thy truth, and when many are carryed about with divers and ſtrange
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 7.</note> doctrines; let us be more and more rooted and ſtabliſhed in the faith, by bringing forth the fruits of righteouſneſs. And
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5, 6, 7.</note> add to our faith virtue; and to virtue knowledge; and to knowledge, temperance; and to temperance, patience; and to patience, godlineſs; and to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, brotherly kindneſs; and to brotherly kindneſs, charity;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 8.</note> that theſe things being in us, we may not be barren, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful in the knowledge of our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95531:27"/>Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, but an entrance may be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 11.</note> unto us abundantly into his everlaſting Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Let the whole race of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind find favour in thine eyes, and let the glorious light of the
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 79.</note> Goſpel of Salvation ſhine upon them that ſit in darkneſs, and the regions of the ſhadow of death. Let the people praiſe
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67. 3.</note> thee, O God; let all the people praiſe thee; call home the Jews, thine ancient people, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the promiſed fulneſs of the Gentiles, that the whole Church may be in Chriſt, as one Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold under one Shepherd.</p>
            <p>O be gracious and favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto Sion, and build up the decayed and ruinous Walls of thy Jeruſalem. Free thy Church from all Hereſie, Prophaneſs,<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95531:28"/>Schiſm, Superſtition and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and whatever is diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in thy ſight, and a blemiſh of the bleſſed Goſpel of God, her Saviour. Keep the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard which thy right hand hath planted, from all its enemies that would pull up the Hedges thereof, and lay it waſte; water
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 3.</note> it every moment, leſt any hurt it, keep it night and day.</p>
            <p>Bleſs theſe Kingdoms of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland</hi> and
<hi>Ireland,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give thoſe many and crying Sins that might make us deſolate without Inhabitants, and let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of us that have added to the great weight of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and made it heavy enough to ſink us into utter ruine, turn from the evil of our ways, and by an hearty repentance, and real reformation ſtand in the<pb n="43" facs="tcp:95531:28"/>gap, and ſtop thoſe Judgments that are gone forth againſt us, and entering in at our wide breaches to deſtroy us: Amend us by thy juſt ſeverities and merciful ſalvations, and let both thy puniſhments and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of us, lead us into the ways of righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Bleſs with thy richeſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings our Sovereign Lord the King, preſerve him, as thou haſt done wonderfully heretofore, from the malice and ſubtlety, the miſchievous Plots and Combinations of his Enemies, and let him ſo remember the deep diſtreſs out of which thou haſt drawn him, and the high authority wherein thou haſt placed him, that in all his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; deſigns, he may promote thy honour and glory, and all
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95531:29"/>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 2.</note> that are under him may lead quiet and peaceable lives, in all godlineſs and honeſty.</p>
            <p>Let the Biſhops and Paſtors of thy Church, further truth and holineſs by their life and Doctrine; and civil Magiſtrates diſcountenance and ſuppreſs all wickedneſs; and encourage vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and goodneſs, and not bear the Sword in vain. And let all from the higheſt to the loweſt, ſo carry themſelves, as that thou mayeſt be glorified, true Religion advanced, the Goſpel of Chriſt honoured, and Truth and Peace may be eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us.</p>
            <p>Let all that are Sick, pained, or impoveriſhed, diſtreſſed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Body or Mind, find thy gracious hand to ſweeten and ſanctifie their Afflictions,<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95531:29"/>and in thy good time to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from them.</p>
            <p>Bleſs us, O our God, that are here before thee, direct, aſſiſt and proſper us in all that we this day ſet our hand unto; and let us not undertake any buſineſs, but what thou haſt warranted by the rules of Righteouſneſs, and upon which we may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and expect thy bleſſing: Guide us by thy Counſel, till
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 24.</note> thou bring us to thy Glory, by Chriſt Jeſus our only Lord and Saviour, who in compaſſion to our Infirmities hath taught us thus to pray;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:95531:30"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:95531:30"/>
            <head>Monday Evening.</head>
            <p>BLeſſed and holy Lord, God, who madeſt all things by thy Power, and ruleſt all things by thy Providence, and filleſt all places by thy preſence, art about our Bed, and about
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 3.</note> our Path, and ſpyeſt out all our Ways; we thy poor Creatures moſt heartily beſeech thee that thou wouldeſt fill every one of our hearts with an awful ſenſe of thee, and an humble ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in our approaches to thee, that laying aſide all guile and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, we may draw near thee
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 22.</note> with a true heart and worſhip thee, that deſireſt truth in the in
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 24.</note> ward part, in Spirit and in Truth.</p>
            <p>We thankfully acknowledge<pb n="48" facs="tcp:95531:31"/>our dependance upon thee, and that our lives, and all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of our lives are the effects of thy bounty and goodneſs thy hands have both made and faſhioned us in the Womb, and brought us into the World, and ever ſince we ſaw the Light, thou haſt all along opened thine hands, and filled us with variety of good things; though for our many and great ſins thou mighteſt have left us na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and miſerable, and brought upon us all the puniſhments, that the threatnings of thy holy and righteous Law have made juſtly due to the Tranſgreſſors of it; and had thy ways been as the ways of a Man are, or thy thoughts towards us like unto our thoughts, we had long ſince been paſt the Thank-offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:95531:31"/>of Praiſe, the benefit of Prayer and the hope of Pardon; for our trangreſſions have been multiplied againſt thee; and our Iniquities have gone over
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. 4.</note> our Heads, as a burthen too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy for us.</p>
            <p>The corruption of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is oppoſite to thy holy Law, that requires no leſs holy prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples than holy practiſes, and by the tranſgreſſions of our lives, we have broken it in thought, word and deed.</p>
            <p>We confeſs, O Lord, with ſorrow and ſhame, our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thy will, and in many things our acting contrary to the knowledge we have had of it, our pride, earthlineſs and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; our injuſtice, uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſs and ſenſuality; our inordinate ſelf-love, eagerneſs in<pb n="50" facs="tcp:95531:32"/>the purſuit of worldly things, and indifferency in matters of Religion; our impenitency and unbelief, the hardneſs of our hearts, notwithſtanding all the ways and methods thou haſt taken to ſoften them; our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſs for all thy mercies, our incorrigibleneſs under all thy chaſtiſements, our unfruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs under the means of Grace, our unfaithfulneſs under all our vows and promiſes, and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſervice and obedience. We have ſinned againſt a clear revelation of thy Will, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the greateſt obligations to compliance with it, againſt the expreſſions of a tender kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in thy multiplyed mercies, and the evidence of a righteous ſeverity in thy juſtly deſerved chaſtiſements; we have ſinned<pb n="51" facs="tcp:95531:32"/>againſt thine inviting promiſes and dreadful threatnings, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the frequent warnings of thy Word, the renewed moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and powerful convictions of thy Spirit, and the precious blood of thy dear Son; we have ſinned againſt the light of our underſtandings, againſt our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and purpoſes of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, againſt the checks of our own conſciences; we cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the number of our ſins, they are ſo exceeding many, nor ſet in order the aggravating cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, whereby they are become exceeding ſinful.</p>
            <p>But, O Lord, have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 1.</note> us, according to thy loving kindneſs: according to the multitude of thy tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies blot out our tranſgreſſions; Help us to forſake our ſinful
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:95531:33"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 7.</note> thoughts and crooked ways, and by unfeigned repentance to return unto thee, that thou mayeſt have mercy on us and abundantly pardon us.</p>
            <p>Speak peace to us, moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Father, through the death and ſufferings of thy dear Son, who gave up himſelf in Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to expiate the guilt of our ſins, and by that precious ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom to buy off the puniſhment that was due to our tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; O ſprinkle our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences with that blood of ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that ſpeaketh better things
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 24.</note> than the blood of
<hi>Abel;</hi> work in us a true and lively faith, that we may be juſtified and have
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1.</note> peace with thee, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: For though we have no righteouſneſs of our own that we dare plead to the<pb n="53" facs="tcp:95531:33"/>ſtrictneſs of thy Law, and the ſeverity of thy Juſtice, thou haſt treaſured up an alſufficient righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in thy Son; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in him we may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and through his ſtripes be healed.</p>
            <p>And let thy pardoning mercy be accompanied with thy pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying grace, that we may be both delivered from the guilt and puniſhment of our ſins, and cleanſed from the filth, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity of them. And as our Lord Chriſt dyed unto ſin to condemn it in the fleſh, let us dye unto ſin to crucific it in ours, that it may never reign in our mortal bodies, that we
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 10, 11, 12.</note> ſhould obey it in the luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>Help us, heavenly Father, to put off the old man, which is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:95531:34"/>corrupt according to deceitful
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 22, 23, 24.</note> luſts, and to put on that new man which is created after thine own image, in righteouſneſs and true holineſs, and as by the natural birth, we have in ſin and corruption born the image of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> that was made a living Soul, ſo let us by the ſpiritual birth, in ſanctification and holineſs, bear the image of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> that was made a quickning Spirit. Give us a new
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 26, 27.</note> heart, and put within us a new Spirit; take away the ſtony heart out of our fleſh, and give us an heart of fleſh; put thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within us, and cauſe us to walk in thy Statutes, that we may keep thy Judgments and do them.</p>
            <p>Wean our hearts from an exceſſive and inordinate love of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:95531:34"/>all the things of this World, and let us never place our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in the pomps and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, the profits and honours, or any tranſitory injoyments of this Life, where we are told not only in thy Word, but by our own experience, it is not to be found; but let us weep, as though we wept not, and
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 30, 31.</note> rejoyce as though we rejoyced not, and buy as though we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed not, and uſe this World as not abuſing it, becauſe the faſhion of this World paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away.</p>
            <p>Let us never adventure upon ſin with the fooliſh and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hopes of getting any thing by it, but let our minds be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenced with the great and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain truth of what our Saviour hath taught us, that the gaining<pb n="56" facs="tcp:95531:35"/>of the whole World, can be
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
16. 26.</note> no recompence for the loſs of our Souls. Let the great and ſtrict account, that we muſt ere long make be often in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thoughts, and the courſe of our Lives be thereby ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that we may think of it with a joyful expectation, and never allow our ſelves to do, to ſpeak or think any thing, that may make the thoughts of the day of Judgment a terrour to us. Let us ſo obey the Laws of our great Lord and Saviour, and follow the ſteps of his example, that when Chriſt, who is our life, ſhall appear, we may lift up our heads with joy, and appear with
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 4.</note> him in glory.</p>
            <p>Show forth the favour and loving kindneſs of a Father, to all the Children of Men, and as<pb n="57" facs="tcp:95531:35"/>thou haſt made them capable of eternal life and happineſs, make known unto them the way of thy Salvation that leads unto it. Let the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ariſe with healing in his
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. 2.</note> Wings, and diſpel the darkneſs of Heatheniſh and Mahometan Superſtition and Idolatry, that the Kingdoms of the Earth may become the Kingdom of thy Son.</p>
            <p>Bleſs thy whole Church, and let the company of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that thou haſt incorporated and knit together as one Body in thy Son, by thy Grace be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſended, and preſerved, enlightned and inſtructed, ordered and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, purged and ſanctified, and let the Ordinances of Chriſt be ſo adminiſtred, and his Laws obſerved, as may become the<pb n="58" facs="tcp:95531:36"/>Spouſe and Body of thy Son.</p>
            <p>Be merciful, O Lord, to the ſinſul Nation wherein we live, and let neither our abuſe of thy mercies, nor our hardning our ſelves under thy Judgments, bring upon us that ruine that they have juſtly deſerved. Lord thou haſt been favourable to the Land, in that thou haſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reſcued us from the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that was due to our Sins, and haſt bleſſed us with the long continuance of thy Goſpel, that was no way due to our walking ſo unworthy of it. Oh let that infinite mercy that hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſpared us, and interpoſed betwixt us and thy deſolating vengeance, forgive our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and turn away the fierceneſs of thine anger.</p>
            <p>Heal our back-ſlidings and<pb n="59" facs="tcp:95531:36"/>heal our breaches, take away
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. 2.</note> all our iniquity, receive us gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly and love us freely, to us belongeth confuſion of Face,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 8. 9.</note> but to the Lord our God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long mercies and forgiveneſſes, though we have rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee. Continue thy mercies, our peace and our plenty, and above all the truth of thy Goſpel and purity of Religion, Cauſe us to fear thee and thy goodneſs, and let thine infinite wiſdom find out a way to bring us out of thoſe woful confuſions, from which to be delivered is above the contrivances of our wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Bleſs with the bleſſings of the right and left hand, of this life, and a better, thine Anointed Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and our Sovereign Lord King
<hi>Charles;</hi> let his Reign be<pb n="60" facs="tcp:95531:37"/>religious, peaceable, long and proſperous; ſo rule his heart in thy faith, fear and love, that he may ever ſeek thy honour and glory. And let all that are Governours under him, in Church or State, exerciſe their power for the puniſhment of
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 14.</note> evil doers, and the praiſe of them that do well.</p>
            <p>Be merciful to all afflicted ones, to our Friends and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to all that have wronged us; forgive our Enemies, O Lord, and help us to forgive them, as we expect to be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven both of them and thee.</p>
            <p>We humbly commit our ſelves to thy merciful protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this night, defend from all danger, our perſons, our dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, our poſſeſſions, refreſh us with a quiet and healthful ſleep,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:95531:37"/>and with the health and ſtrength of our Bodies, and the vigour of our minds, let us ſerve thee all our days, till at the end of them we receive the end of our Faith, the ſalvation of our Souls, through thy dear Son, our alone Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt, in the merit of whoſe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and interceſſion we fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pray:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:95531:38"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:95531:38"/>
            <head>Tueſday Morning.</head>
            <p>GReat and glorious Lord God, who art infinite and incomprehenſible in all perfections, art cloathed with Glory and Majeſty, and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt in that light that no mortal creature can approach and live, we thine unworthy ſervants, humbly ſenſible of our infinite diſtance as creatures, and our abominable vileneſs as Sinners, are here before thee this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to offer up our prayers and praiſes in the Name and Mediation of thy Son. In our ſelves we have no confidence to appear before thee, for we are as dry ſtubble, and thou a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire, but in thy beloved
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:95531:39"/>Son, our ever bleſſed Redeemer and Interceſſor we have acceſs with confidence, who hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10, 19, 20.</note> an entrance into the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt by his Blood, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated a new and living way to the Throne of thy Grace, through the Veil of his Fleſh, that we coming to thee, in his precious and prevailing Name,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. ult.</note> may obtain mercy and find grace to help in our time of need.</p>
            <p>We are guilty Sinners and want pardon, we are defiled Sinners and want cleanſing, we are weak Sinners and want ſtrengthning, we are fooliſh Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and want to be inſtructed in the ways of thy Word, and wandring Sinners that want to be brought back into them, but though our caſe be all neceſſity,<pb n="65" facs="tcp:95531:39"/>thy glorious attribute is Al-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, and thy grace and mercy, thy wiſdom and power, is ready to ſupply all our wants
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 19.</note> according to thy riches in glory by Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>We admire with all thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thy great patience and long-ſuffering towards us, that thou haſt hitherto ſpared us, and not ſpeedily brought upon us that puniſhment and miſery that our ſins have righteouſly deſerved, of which we can give no account, but that thou art merciful, becauſe mercy pleaſes thee, and ſheweſt compaſſion, becauſe thou delighteſt in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion: but ſuch is thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thou haſt not only ſpared but bountifully ſupplyed us, and given us all things richly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, that belong to life and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:95531:40"/>thou feedeſt and cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt us, preſerveſt and defendeſt us, haſt ſafely brought us through the darkneſs and the dangers of the laſt night to the light of another day; for theſe and all the bleſſings of this life, we praiſe thee, but we much more magnifie and adore thine inconceiveable goodneſs and love in giving us thy Son to redeem us from wrath and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and thy holy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel to conduct us in the way to eternal life. And we cannot without confuſion of face, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the ſhameful and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuous returns we have made of thine abundant and undeſerved kindneſſes, that when thou haſt nouriſhed and brought up children, we have rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 2.</note> thee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:95531:40"/>Thy holy Laws we have broken in ſinful thoughts, words and actions, though thou haſt therein commanded us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is in it ſelf juſt, and reaſonable, and what is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to our dependance upon thy holy Majeſty, we have not carried our ſelves as it becomes us, to thee, in holineſs and godlineſs; to our neighbours in righteouſneſs and charity; to our ſelves in temperance and ſobriety; but have followed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and fulfilled the ſenſual ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites and inclinations of our own hearts, and inſtead of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thee, our God, have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved divers luſts and pleaſures.</p>
            <p>We have known that our vile bodies muſt ere long lye down in the houſe of duſt and rottenneſs, and yet we have<pb n="68" facs="tcp:95531:41"/>pampered them to fulfil the luſts of our fleſh; and that our immortal Souls muſt laſt an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of Happineſs or Miſery, and yet we have neglected lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up in ſtore for them, an Happineſs in the future State<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 27.</note> And while we have laboured for the meat that periſhes, we hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neglected that which endure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto everlaſting Life. We hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> little conſidered the great en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our coming into this world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and as little laid to heart wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will become of us when w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall go hence and be no mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and as though we were to dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the Beaſts dye, we have liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> too much as the Beaſts live.</p>
            <p>In our ſelves, O Lord, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have no hope, but in the mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude of thy tender mercies w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot deſpair, and thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:95531:41"/>we have deſerved wrath and vengeance, and have nothing of our own to plead, why we ſhould eſcape it, we are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encouraged to ſue to thine offended Majeſty for pardon and forgiveneſs, by that Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation which thou haſt made
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 6, 7.</note> of thy glorious Name, the Lord, the Lord God, merciful and gracious, long-ſuffering and abundant in goodneſs, and truth, keeping mercy for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and forgiving iniquity, and tranſgreſſion, and ſin, and becauſe thou haſt ſaid thou wilt not clear the guilty, take away our guilt by a ſincere hearty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and a true and lively faith in the merits, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of thy Son.</p>
            <p>Let all our ſins be more bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and burthenſom in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:95531:42"/>of them, than they have ever been pleaſant and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the commiſſion of them, and grant, gracious Lord, that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e may be ſo ſorrowful for
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſins, as to loath them, ſo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them, as to take up firm Reſolutions againſt them, and ſo reſolve, as that by the powerful aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit, we may never renew the practice of them, and having done ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 34. 32.</note> we may do ſo and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend no more.</p>
            <p>Waſh and cleanſe our ſinful Souls, from their guilt and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs in that fountain of thy dear Sons moſt precious blood,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 13. 1.</note> which thou haſt ſet open for ſin, and uncleanneſs, and by the grace of thy holy Spirit, ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and mortifying our ſins in us, convince and ſatisfie us that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:95531:42"/>thou haſt pardoned them: cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in us clean hearts, O God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 10.</note> and renew right ſpirits within us.</p>
            <p>And as we call thy Son, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, our Saviour, and hope to be for ever happy in the light and injoyment of him in Heaven, let us make him our example, and purifie our ſelves even as he is pure.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 3.</note> Make us as he was, holy and humble, meek and merciful, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and charitable, heavenly minded and ſelf-denying: let's be zealous for thy glory, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with our preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſatisfied with all the wiſe allotments of thy providence, and make it our meat and drink to do the will of our heavenly Father; and in all things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was a moſt lively and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:95531:43"/>pattern for our imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſeeing we profeſs our ſelves Chriſtians, and ſay we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 6.</note> in him, let us walk as he alſo walked.</p>
            <p>Settle and root in our hearts a ſtronger and more firm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of thy holy Goſpel, and ſo fix our thoughts and affections upon that unſeen happineſs, that our Saviour in our name and place is poſſeſſed of; that nothing here below may either allure or affright us from our duty or make us remiſs, cold and negligent in it, but we may be zealous of good works, and with fervency of ſpirit alway ſerve that gracious Lord, from whom we expect the reward of a glorious and immortal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</p>
            <p>Fill every one of our hearts<pb n="73" facs="tcp:95531:43"/>with a quick and a conſtant ſenſe, an humble and awful dread, an ardent and intire love of thee, together with an active and vigorous delight in thee, and a vigilant and circumſpect care univerſally, and in the whole courſe of our lives, to pleaſe and approve our ſelves to thee. Let us never adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to commit any ſin, as a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle one, becauſe it will offend and diſhonour thee, the great and infinite Majeſty of Heaven, and deſerve the eternal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and miſery of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Soul.</p>
            <p>Keep us by thy grace from every evil way; and thoſe ſins eſpecially to the which we may be moſt inclined, and eaſily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon by cuſtom or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; the naughtineſs and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral<pb n="74" facs="tcp:95531:44"/>corruption of the age we live in, our Callings, our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany or our conſtitution, ſo that laying aſide every weight,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 2.</note> and the ſins that eaſily beſet us, and running with patience and perſeverance the race that thou haſt ſet before us, we may at length obtain that prize of our High Calling, which thou haſt prepared and promiſed in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>And in his Name we humbly recommend to thy compaſſion and goodneſs, all the Sons of Men that dwell upon the Face of the Earth, beſeeching thee that thou wouldſt make known thy Will to them, and help them to practiſe according to what they know, and whatever affliction or calamity may lye upon them in mind, body or<pb n="75" facs="tcp:95531:44"/>eſtate, let them by thy mercy and clemency, be ſupported un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, and in thy due time be delivered from them.</p>
            <p>Shew favourable regards of care and kindneſs towards thy Church, engrave her upon the Palms of thine Hands, and let
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 16.</note> her Walls be continually before thee.</p>
            <p>Appoint Salvation for the Walls and Bulwarks of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherein we live, pardon our many crying ſins, avert thy deſerved, feared Judgments, heal our back-ſlidings, and heal our breaches, continue thy Goſpel, and grant that we may walk worthy of that ineſtimable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
            <p>Bleſs our dread Sovereign with the bleſſings of thy right and left hand, let his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<pb n="76" facs="tcp:95531:45"/>be happy and peaceable, long and proſperous, and a publick bleſſing to all that are under it, and grant that all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Governours in Church, in State, may faithfully uſe their power to the diſcouragement of Vice and ungodlineſs, and the promoting and ſupporting peace and good order, truth, righteouſneſs and holineſs: and let all men by a ſerious repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and a through reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their ways, ſtrive to ſave the Land from thoſe confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and miſeries, into which they have plunged it by their manifold offences. Comfort all that mourn, give them beauty for aſhes, and the garments of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſs, and let all that groan under thy heavy hand triumph in thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:95531:45"/>Be with us thy ſervants, this day, and let that good provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that hath this night pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and refreſhed us, direct, aſſiſt and bleſs us in all our ways, and keep us from the dangers and miſchiefs, the ſins and offences, the ſnares and temptations that we might o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe fall into. Let us be in thy fear all the day long, and ſo order our lives, as if it were the laſt day we had to live in this world, that as in the evening we ſhall be one day nearer our death, we may be nearer eternal life and happineſs; grant us all theſe our requeſts, moſt gracious Father, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe thou knoweſt to be needful for us, for the ſake of thy dear Son, in whoſe Name and Words, by his own direction<pb n="78" facs="tcp:95531:46"/>we further implore thy merciful goodneſs;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:95531:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Tueſday Evening.</head>
            <p>ALmighty and moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful God and Father, the Maker and Governour of all Creatures in Heaven and Earth, and exalted in thy glorious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, above the thoughts and ſervices, the praiſes and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments of the higheſt and beſt of them, thine under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is infinite, and thou ſeeſt the hearts and ways of all the ſons of men, thy holineſs is infinite, and thou hateſt all the ſin and iniquity thou eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in them, thy power infinite, &amp; thou canſt eaſily puniſh them for the ſins that provoke and diſpleaſe thee, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yet thine infinite mercies thou pardoneſt<pb n="80" facs="tcp:95531:47"/>the ſins of all that by ſincere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and a through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of their ways return to thee.</p>
            <p>We thy poor Servants in a deep ſenſe of our guilt and wretchedneſs, and the ſtrong en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements of thy declared mercy and goodneſs, humble our Souls at thy Foot-ſtool, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching thee to have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and through the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of thy dear Son, whom thou haſt given to be a propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, and price of redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for us, to pardon our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great tranſgreſſions, whereof we are guilty before thy Majeſty, in thought, and word, and deed, and whereby we have deſerved to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with overlaſting deſtruction, from thy preſence, by thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious power.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:95531:47"/>Hadſt thou, O Lord, taken advantages againſt us, or been forward to pour out that wrath and vengeance that we have been forward to provoke, we had not now been begging thy mercy, or cheriſh'd with the hopes of it, but had in vain la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the bloody and ſevere effects of thine incenſed Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>We are not only by Nature the Children of Wrath, but have in the courſe of our Lives actuated the ſinful, corrupt principles of our Nature, and gone aſtray from thy holy, juſt and good Laws, that thou haſt given to be the rule and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our actions: and though both as thy Creatures, thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and thy Children, thou haſt laid upon us the greateſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:95531:48"/>obligations to obedience, and a dutyful complyance with thy Will, yet have we in the eager and violent purſuit of our luſts
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 3.</note> broken thy bonds aſunder, and caſt away thy cords from us.</p>
            <p>We have profeſſed the pure and holy Religion of thy Son, but have ſhamefully diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him and his Religion, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure and unholy practiſes, and
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19.</note> naming the Name of Chriſt, we have not departed from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: we have given up our Names to him in Baptiſm, and ſolemnly vowed obedience to the Laws of his holy Goſpel, but we have ſtarted aſide, like broken Bows, and walked in the imaginations of our own hearts, and fulfilled our vile and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh luſts, as if there were no God to be ſerved, no Soul to be <pb n="83" facs="tcp:95531:48"/>ſaved, no Hell to be feared, no Heaven to be expected, and as if the Name of Chriſtians would have carryed us to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, we have done thoſe things that many Heathens would have bluſhed at and been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed to have practiſed; ſo that this might be our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, which of all other is the moſt grievous and inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable, that Light is come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, and we have lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Darkneſs rather than Light,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 19.</note> becauſe our deeds have been evil.</p>
            <p>So many, and undeſerved, have been thy mercies towards us, ſo kind and unwearied the expreſſions of thy bounty, that all our diſobedience is by a ſhameful and odious ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude become exceeding ſinful,<pb n="84" facs="tcp:95531:49"/>and we cannot without ſorrow of heart and confuſion of Face, reflect upon our wearying thee with our ſins, when thou haſt loaded us with thy benefits.</p>
            <p>But we beſeech thee, O moſt merciful Father, in the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt compaſſions of thy ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bowels, look down upon us, and for thy Names ſake (the moſt powerful argument and ſuch as uſes to prevail) O Lord hear, O Lord ſpare, O Lord forgive: by a ſerious and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty repentance, and a true and lively Faith in thy Son, make us fit partakers of thy pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy.</p>
            <p>Though our deſerts are thine indignation and vengeance, the merit of his righteouſneſs is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and forgiveneſs, though we have affronted thy Juſtice,<pb n="85" facs="tcp:95531:49"/>he hath ſatisfied it, though we have incenſed thy wrath, he hath appeaſed it; the chaſtiſement of
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 5.</note> our peace was upon him; O let the merit of his righteouſneſs be upon us.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the holy Jeſus, together with the guilt and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſin, alway delivers from the power of it, and they that are Chriſts, crucifie the
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 24.</note> fleſh with its affections and luſts, by the ſubduing and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of our ſins, convince and comfortably ſatisfie us that thou haſt pardoned them, and by thy ſanctifying grace, help us to cleanſe our ſelves from
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1.</note> all filthineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit, and to perfect holineſs in thy fear: ſanctifie us whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 23.</note> and let our whole ſpirit, and ſoul, and body be preſerved<pb n="86" facs="tcp:95531:50"/>blameleſs, unto the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Quicken us, holy Father by the ſpirit of life and holineſs, to run the ways of thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and as thou haſt given our bleſſed Saviour to be Head of thy Church, and anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with an unmeaſured fulneſs of thy Spirit, that he might communicate and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part it to the Members of his Body, let ſome drops of that holy Oil fall down upon us, that was ſo plentifully poured upon the Head of our High Prieſt, and out of his fulneſs, let us receive
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 16.</note> Grace for Grace; and ſo renew the Image of his Holineſs in our Souls, that as his true Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren we may ſhew forth all the Features and Lineaments of our heavenly Father.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:95531:50"/>And becauſe we are not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient of our ſelves, to avoid any evil, or perform any good, be graciouſly preſent with us to preſerve us from the one, and aſſiſt us in the other. Make us perfect in every good work, to do thy will, working in us that which is well pleaſing in
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 21.</note> thy ſight through Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Make us wiſe to Salvation, and ſeeing our days are very few and uncertain, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance both neceſſary and out of our own power, let us not put it off till to morrow, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what a day may bring forth, nor deceive our ſelves with vain purpoſes of parting with our Sins hereafter, when this very night our Souls may be
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 20.</note> taken from us; But ſeeing the Heavens and the Earth at <pb n="88" facs="tcp:95531:51"/>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 15.</note> length, and our ſelves ere long, muſt be diſſolved, let us be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, that we may be found of thee in peace, without ſpot, and blameleſs.</p>
            <p>Bleſs thy whole Church ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered far and near over the Face of the Earth; pour out upon it the Spirit of Truth and Holineſs, and grant that all that confeſs thy holy Name, may agree in the truth of thy holy Word, and live in unity and godly love; be thou that art the Lord and Lawgiver of thy Church and People, their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and Saviour from all their Enemies, thou art our
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. 4.</note> King, O God, command deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances for <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be gracious and favourable to theſe Nations, many and heinous are the ſins whereby<pb n="89" facs="tcp:95531:51"/>we have provoked thy Majeſty, great and heavy the Judgments that hang over us for thoſe Sins; pardon we moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee our Sins, and avert thoſe Judgments, thou that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt between the Cherubims ſhine forth; before <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſtir up thy
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80. 1, 2.</note> ſtrength, and come and ſave us.</p>
            <p>And though we of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have deſerved to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown with an utter deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and for ever caſt out of thy ſight, as a loathſome and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable thing; for thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, O Lord, pardon and ſpare, reform and amend, compoſe and ſettle, heal and eſtabliſh us, in the multitude of thy tender mercies.</p>
            <p>Give us not up to the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs<pb n="90" facs="tcp:95531:52"/>and deſolations that we have deſerved, and thine and our Enemies have deſigned, nor ſuffer thoſe that hate us proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſult and triumph over us.</p>
            <p>Bleſs with all bleſſings of this life and the next, thine anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Servant our Sovereign Lord the King; direct him in ſuch ways as are pleaſing to thee, and protect him from all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that may at any time threaten him. Let all ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Miniſters Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, be ſo aſſiſted by thy Grace and holy Spirit, that Religion and Godlineſs, Peace and Order, Love and Unity, Truth and Righteouſneſs may be eſtabliſhed and encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1.</note> among us, and let all ſorts of men, laying aſide <pb n="91" facs="tcp:95531:52"/>all malice, and all guile, and hypocriſies, and envies, and all evil ſpeakings, keep the unity
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 3.</note> of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace.</p>
            <p>Comfort the afflicted and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed in Mind, Body or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, recompenſe the kindneſſes of our Friends ſeven fold into their Boſoms, forgive our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and help us ſo to forgive them, that we may comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hope for our own forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Keep us, O Lord, from the evils and dangers, that, without thy protection might this night befal us, refreſh and ſtrengthen our frail Bodies with a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, quiet and peaceable reſt, and let the ſtrength of this nights healthful repoſe, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to thee in the next
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:95531:53"/>days faithful ſervice, that as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day we are nearer our death; we may be nearer an immortal Crown of Life and Glory, which thou haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and promiſed to them that Love and Fear thee, through Jeſus Chriſt, who, by his Righteouſneſs and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, hath given us the liberty and confidence to ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:95531:53"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:95531:54"/>
            <head>Wedneſday Morning.</head>
            <p>HOly and heavenly Father, thou art infinite in Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Wiſdom, in Holineſs, Truth and Goodneſs, abundant in Mercy to all that call upon thee in truth, all thy Works in Heaven and Earth ſhew forth thy praiſe; the glorious Angels, and the glorified Spirits of juſt Men, being themſelves honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the honouring of thee, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſtingly triumph in the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of thy divine &amp; incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible perfections; to praiſe and magnifie thy great and holy Name, is both the duty and priviledge of the Sons of Men, to whom thou haſt given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings in ſome meaſure<pb n="95" facs="tcp:95531:54"/>to conceive thy glorious excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, and tongues to declare them.</p>
            <p>We thy poor and unworthy Servants, humbly offer up to thy divine Majeſty, the tribute of our hearty praiſes, and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of thine infinite Power and Juſtice, Wiſdom and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Truth and Faithfulneſs, and bleſs thee with our whole Souls, for all thoſe bleſſings for our Souls and Bodies, our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and future happineſs, which are the effects of thy bounty and goodneſs.</p>
            <p>We thank thee, O Lord, for our health and ſtrength, our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and peace, the Bread we eat and the Raiment we put on, that thou haſt delivered us from Pains and Sickneſſes, and thoſe grievous preſſures and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<pb n="96" facs="tcp:95531:55"/>wherewith others, better than our ſelves, are ſorely affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that thou haſt the laſt night preſerved us from dangers and refreſhed us with ſleep, and beſtoweſt upon us all the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and conveniencies of Life, and above all, that thou haſt redeemed us from Hell and Damnation, by the precious Blood of thy dear Son, that by his Goſpel thou haſt brought to light life and immortality, and encouraged our hopes of them, by thy precious and faithful promiſes.</p>
            <p>Lord what is Man that thou art ſo mindful of him? What are Sinners that thou ſheweſt ſuch favour unto them? Thy mercies conferr'd upon us are admirable, as we are thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that can no way oblige
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:95531:55"/>our Almighty and Independent Creator, and much more ſo as we are Sinners, that have offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and provoked our moſt righteous Sovereign Lord and Lawgiver.</p>
            <p>Ever ſince we came into the World, we have been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with a contagious Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie and loathſom Diſeaſe, and have added the iniquities of practiſe to our natural pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and more defiled our ſelves by chuſing our own crooked ways, and fulfilling the imaginations of our naughty hearts.</p>
            <p>We have many times given ſcandal to others, by our open and obſerved miſcarriages, and caſt a blemiſh and reproach upon that holy Religion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we have made profeſſion;<pb n="98" facs="tcp:95531:56"/>ſo as to have made it worſe thought on by its Enemies, and with great folly we have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times adventur'd to commit thoſe Sins in our private retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which we would have been aſhamed that men ſhould have taken notice of, though we have well known that the
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 12</note> light and darkneſs are both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to thee, and that no ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie can hide from thine all-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eye.</p>
            <p>We have been too careleſs of avoiding temptations to Sin, and have run into thoſe ſnares, that by taking heed to our feet, we might have avoided; we have neglected the means of mortifying our Luſts, watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Prayer and Faſting, which through thy bleſſing might have been effectual to that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<pb n="99" facs="tcp:95531:56"/>purpoſe, and inſtead of ſtrongly and reſolutely oppoſing we have cowardly and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly complied with, furniſhed and animated thine and our Enemies, making proviſion for
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 14.</note> our Fleſh, to fulfil the Luſts thereof: and though we have been well aſſured that our lives and all our preſent earthly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments that ſupport and ſweeten them, are but of a ſhort and momentany continuance, we have laboured &amp; been ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 27.</note> for the meat that periſhes and neglected that which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures to everlaſting Life.</p>
            <p>How often have we deafned our Ear to the calls of thy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel? And made light of both the invitations of thy gracious promiſes, and the terrors of thy dreadful threatnings? How of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten<pb n="100" facs="tcp:95531:57"/>have we hardned our hearts againſt the motions of thy holy Spirit? How often to ſatisfie our luſtful appetites, have we broken through the convictions of our own conſciences? And to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late thy holy and good Laws, have offered violence to the dictates of our own minds?</p>
            <p>We judge our ſelves, O Lord, and acknowledge we have juſtly deſerved all that wrath that might make us everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſerable, and made our ſelves liable to thoſe threatned puniſhments, which we can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eſcape nor endure; but O our merciful Father, do not thou condemn us, we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed and confounded in the ſenſe and remembrance of our tranſgreſſions, comfort us, O Lord, we beſeech thee, with a
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:95531:57"/>ſenſe of thy pardoning mercy, in our bleſſed and all-ſufficient Redeemer.</p>
            <p>Help us by a ſincere and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty repentance, to return to thee, from whom in our own crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and perverſe ways we have gone aſtray; Let the time paſt of our lives ſuffice us to have
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 3.</note> wrought the wills of the fleſh, and ſeeing we have already by the frequent commiſſions of ſin too much offended thee, and endangered our Souls, let us not by the repeated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued practice of it, heighten the offence and add to our guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs.</p>
            <p>Let the Blood of thy dear
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 7.</note> Son Jeſus Chriſt cleanſe us from all ſin, and through his precious Sacrifice and meritorious ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that was pure and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb n="102" facs="tcp:95531:58"/>innocent, diſcharge and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit us that have been foul of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders.</p>
            <p>Let thy holy Spirit ſanctifie and renew us after thine own Image, in righteouſneſs and true holineſs, and as we hope to be pardoned, by the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous death of Chriſt, grant that crucifying our Luſts upon his Croſs; we may follow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his holy Life, and in all holineſs and humility, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and charity, zeal for thy Glory and ſubmiſſion to thy Will, patience, heavenly mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and ſelf-denial, content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the contempt of this World, we may walk as Chriſt walked, and be filled with all
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 11.</note> the fruits of righteouſneſs, which are through him unto thy praiſe and glory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:95531:58"/>Help us to live by faith in thy promiſes, in all varieties of thy providence, let this be our great ſupport and comfort, that thou haſt ſaid thou wilt never
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5.</note> leave us nor forſake us, and in all difficulties and temptations, let this be our great care, that we do not leave nor forſake thee, But ſanctifie the Lord God
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 15.</note> in our hearts, and with a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous faithfulneſs endeavour to pleaſe and approve our ſelves to thee in all our ways; and ſeeing we call on the Father, who, without reſpect of perſons judges according to every mans work, let us paſs the time of our ſojourning here in fear:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 17.</note> And give diligence to make our calling and election ſure, that
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10, 11.</note> we may never fall either into ſcandalous ſins or inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<pb n="104" facs="tcp:95531:59"/>miſeries, but an entrance may be miniſtred to us abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 4.</note> and when Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, we may alſo appear with him in glory.</p>
            <p>Shew thy favour and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to all mankind, and grant, O Lord, we beſeech thee, that the courſe of this world may be ſo peaceably ordered by thy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance, that thy Church may joyſully ſerve thee in all godly quietneſs, and being delivered from the Plots and Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Oppoſitions and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of its Enemies, may alway walk before thee in truth and holineſs, and all that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Goſpel of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, may hold faſt his pure and heavenly Doctrines, and expreſs
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:95531:59"/>the power of them in their lives.</p>
            <p>Bleſs this ſinful and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Nation, wherein we live, pardon our many great and crying ſins, heal our wide breaches, unite our diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, compoſe our diſtractions, and remove from us whatever may provoke the Eyes of thy Jealouſie and Glory, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of thy long continued temporal and ſpiritual bleſſings, and lay us open to thy dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and deſolating Judgments.</p>
            <p>Send thy bleſſed Spirit into our hearts, a ſpirit of wiſdom and knowledge, and of the fear of the Lord, a ſpirit of truth and holineſs, of peace and unity, of righteouſneſs, moderation, meekneſs and charity, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of loading one another<pb n="106" facs="tcp:95531:60"/>with ſlanders and ſcandals, foul reproaches and bitter cenſures, help us to bear one anothers
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 2.</note> burdens, and ſo fulfil the Law of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Bleſs our Sovereign Lord King <hi>Charles</hi> with the choiceſt of thy bleſſings, fill his heart with wiſdom and piety, with a mighty ſenſe of the great Truſt thou haſt committed to him, and the great obligations thou haſt laid upon him, with courage and reſolution to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and promote Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and true Religion.</p>
            <p>And grant that all in places of Power and Authority may exert, and uſe it for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of evil doers, and the praiſe of them that do well, as it becomes them that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their Power from thee,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:95531:60"/>and are accountable for it unto thee. Order all publick Affairs to thy glory, and the comfort and encouragement of all that fear thee. Support and comfort all thoſe whom thou haſt fed with the Bread of Tears and mingled their drink with weeping.</p>
            <p>And we humbly beſeech thee for a bleſſing upon our ſelves, as thou haſt preſerved us this night, direct, aſſiſt, and proſper us in all the affairs and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes of this day, and let us all the day long be in thy fear, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring thou obſerveſt, and thou wilt judge us: and let a ſenſe of this preſerve us from all ſin, and quicken us to the doing of whatever may be pleaſing in thy ſight, through our bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, who, when we pray, hath taught and commanded us to ſay;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:95531:61"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:95531:61"/>
            <head>Wedneſday Evening.</head>
            <p>BLeſſed Lord God, the high and lofty One, that inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biteſt
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57. 15.</note> eternity, whoſe Name is Holy, who dwelleſt in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of a contrite and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit. We wretched and miſerable ſinners, moſt humbly beſeech thee to look down upon us from the habitation of thy Holineſs, and glory in the multitude of thy tender mercies; and work in us that humble and contrite Spirit, that is ſo pleaſing and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in thy ſight, that our hearts, hardned by the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sin, may be ſoftned by the effectual working of thy Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:95531:62"/>By commanding us to call upon thee, thou haſt made Prayer our Duty, and by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to hear us when we Pray, thou haſt made it no leſs our priviledge: in obedience to thy command, and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of thy Promiſe, we are here before thee, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up our Evening Sacrifice of Prayer, deſiring thee both to prepare our Hearts to Pray, and bow down thine ear to hear.</p>
            <p>We are not of our ſelves ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to perform any duty, to bear any burden, to reſiſt any temptation, to mortifie any luſt,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5.</note> To think one good thought, but all our ſufficiency is of thee: thou, O Lord, canſt pardon our Sins, ſupply our wants, heal our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, enlighten our blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſoften our hardneſs,<pb n="111" facs="tcp:95531:62"/>ſtrengthen our weakneſs, we have no whither to go but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, nor can we come to thee but in thine own Power: into ſuch a wretched condition have our Sins, brought us, that we are both unable to help our ſelves, and unworthy that thou ſhouldſt help us; but our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, that thy Grace doth not uſe to find Sinners worthy, but make them ſo, nor doſt thou ſhew favour and kindneſs to them, becauſe they pleaſe thee, but becauſe thou art pleaſed with thine own Mercy and Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>Our Iniquities, we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, have been many and great, a ſinful nature, as a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Fountain, hath ſent forth polluted ſtreams in the thoughts, words and actions of our Lives,<pb n="112" facs="tcp:95531:63"/>and we have often offended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy holy Laws, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the enmity of our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal minds. Though all thy Laws are in themſelves moſt equal, juſt and good, and thou haſt both encouraged our obedience by the gracious promiſes of thy favourable acceptance, and an eternal recompence; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted from ſin by threatning it with everlaſting puniſhment, yet lightly eſteeming thy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and contemning thy threatnings, we have trodd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n thy holy Laws under our Feet, and broken through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints, wherewith
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ou haſt hedged us in from finding our own ways.</p>
            <p>Our pride and earthlineſs, our unbelief &amp; unthankfulneſs, our hypocriſie, ſenſuality and<pb n="113" facs="tcp:95531:63"/>hardneſs of heart, witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us to our faces, and give us great cauſe to bluſh and be confounded, to mourn and grieve in the ſenſe of them.</p>
            <p>Who of us hath had that due ſenſe of thy holineſs, power and goodneſs, thine omnipreſence and all-ſeeing Eye, as to be thereby driven from our Sins, or quickned to the exerciſe of Virtue and Godlineſs? Who of us hath been ſo affected with that Grace that hath appeared bringing Salvation, as to deny un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs and worldly luſts, and make it our ſtudy and buſineſs to pleaſe and approve our ſelves to thee? Who of us hath ſo felt the burthen, and taſted the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs of our ſins, as to loath and leave them with diſlike and abhorrency? Who of us hath
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:95531:64"/>been ſo delighted in thy love, as to return thee our hearty love in a ſincere and uniform obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? Who of us hath ſo firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed the rewards and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments of the future ſtate, as to preſs toward the mark for the obtaining the prize, and make haſt to eſcape and flee from the bottomleſs Pit and burning Lake?</p>
            <p>The zeal and earneſtneſs that we ſhould have ſhewn in matters of Religion, we have expreſſed in following our worldly intereſts, and that cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and indifferency that would have been well beſtowed upon the little and ſhort lived bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of the preſent Life, hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the performance of our holy duties.</p>
            <p>We have in ſome meaſure<pb n="115" facs="tcp:95531:64"/>known our Maſters Will, and yet have done our own, and to pleaſe our corrupt and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Appetites, have done what we have well underſtood to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing in thy ſight. Though thou haſt often commanded us to repent, and turn from our evil ways, and we have been convinced that to hear thy Voice to day, is both our duty and our wiſdom, we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murred by lingring delays, and not caſt off our Sins by a ſpeedy repentance.</p>
            <p>We are aſhamed, O Lord, of this our folly, and beſeech thee ſo to awaken and aſſiſt us by thy Grace, that we may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it in vain, nor longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude our own Souls with the deceitful purpoſes of a future re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, but let us make haſte<pb n="116" facs="tcp:95531:65"/>to hearken to thy loud and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2.</note> Calls, now while it is the accepted time, and the day of Salvation.</p>
            <p>And let thy pardoning mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy freely forgive all our Sins, thy Grace having by true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance made us meet parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of that ineſtimable benefit: So ſet them before our face, as that we may mark and conſider them, mourn for and confeſs, loath and forſake them; and ſo caſt them behind thy back, as not to obſerve them with a wrathful countenance, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them with a juſtly deſerved vengeance.</p>
            <p>By the precious blood of thy dear Son, that immaculate Lamb, that was offered to take away the Sins of the World,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 2.</note> Waſh us throughly from our <pb n="117" facs="tcp:95531:65"/>Iniquities, and cleanſe us from our Sins, and through his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect righteouſneſs let the free gift come upon us unto juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 18.</note> of Life.</p>
            <p>Deliver us, we pray thee, as from the guilt and damnation of Sin by his precious Sacrifice ſo from its power and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by his ſanctifying Spirit, and though like a Leprofie in the Walls of an infected houſe, Sin will remain in us while we are in the world, let it not reign
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 12.</note> in our mortal Body, that we ſhould obey it in the luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But as the Fleſh in us lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth againſt the Spirit, let thy
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 17.</note> Spirit in us reſiſt and ſubdue the luſts of the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>Let not an inordinate love of the allurements, and intangling vanities of this World quench<pb n="118" facs="tcp:95531:66"/>or weaken in our Souls that entire and moſt hearty love that is due to thee and heavenly things, nor diſtracting cares for the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of the Body, eat out and deſtroy the care of our Souls, nor hinder a timely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for their future and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs. But for as much as our ſtay here below is very ſhort, and the time of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture hence into an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſtate very uncertain, let us with fear and trembling, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs and diligence, work out our own Salvation, and carry our ſelves with upright and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive Conſciences toward thee and all men whilſt we are in the World, as we ſhall wiſh to have done when we come to leave it.</p>
            <p>Help us to run the race of<pb n="119" facs="tcp:95531:66"/>holy obedience, meekneſs and patience, charity, contentment, conſtancy and perſeverance, to fight a good fight, finiſh our courſe, and keep the faith, that we may receive a Crown of righteouſneſs, which the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge ſhall at the laſt day
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7. 8.</note> give unto all them that love his appearing: And let the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of that glory and happineſs, and the well-ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hope of our attaining it, make us diligent and faithful in the diſcharge of our duty, watchful againſt all fleſhly defilements, patient and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful under all croſſes and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, cold and indifferent to all the profits and pleaſures of this Life, and let our whole conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation on Earth be ſuch as may become the Heirs of an heavenly,<pb n="120" facs="tcp:95531:67"/>glorious and eternal inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: that when our earthly
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1.</note> houſe of this tabernacle ſhall be diſſolved, we may have a build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and be found meet to be
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 12.</note> partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in Light.</p>
            <p>Look in mercy upon all the Sons of Men, and cauſe the light of thy Goſpel to guide their feet into the way of peace, that are wandring in the darkneſs of ſenſuality, profaneneſs, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and idolatry, and ſhew them thy Salvation.</p>
            <p>Bleſs thy whole Church throughout the World; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it from the offences and reproachful ſcandals of its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Friends, and from the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and perſecutions of its<pb n="121" facs="tcp:95531:67"/>open and declared Enemies: Let thy continual care keep and cleanſe thy Vineyard, that it may abound in the Fruits of Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Be merciful to this Nation where we live, pardon the Sins that cry aloud for vengeance, heal the breaches that threaten its ruine, and avert thoſe dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Judgments that hang over our heads; and as thou haſt all along often ſaved us from the deſtructions &amp; miſeries that our daring wickedneſſes might have pull'd down upon our heads, give us cauſe more and more to magnifie thy mercy, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in thy Salvation.</p>
            <p>Bleſs our Lord the King with Wiſdom and Courage, a zeal for thy glory, and a continual care of promoting Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:95531:68"/>and true Religion; and let all under him in places of Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Government, make it their buſineſs to further Righteouſneſs and Peace, and the good of Souls: and let all ſorts of men follow after peace, without which they cannot ſee happineſs on Earth, and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without which they ſhall not ſee thy Face in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Be thou a preſent help for the relief and ſuccour of all that are in a ſuffering condition, and let that good providence that hath defended, directed and aſſiſted us in the dangers, the occurrences and buſineſſes of the day, ſo protect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh us with ſleep this night, that in the morning we may be more fit to ſerve thee, and live to thy praiſe in Chriſt Jeſus our<pb n="123" facs="tcp:95531:68"/>Lord, through whom, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to accept our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, pardon our ſins and hear our Prayers, when we ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:95531:69"/>
            <head>Thurſday Morning.</head>
            <p>MOſt gracious God, and merciful Father in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the Author of our Being, and the Fountain of all thoſe good things that may make us happy in this World and that which is to come, we thy poor Creatures, vile and provoking Sinners, in the ſenſe of our own guilt fly to thy mercy to pardon us; in the ſenſe of our weakneſs fly to thy might to ſtrengthen us; in the ſenſe of our own ignorance and folly, fly to thy wiſdom to inſtruct and counſel us; in the ſenſe of our manifold wants and neceſſities, fly to thy fulneſs and all-ſufficiency to ſupply us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:95531:69"/>We acknowledge, O Lord, that our nature is not only cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and ſinful, overſpread with a Leproſie and loathſome Diſeaſe, that might make us for ever abominable in thy pure Eyes; but our practiſes have been contrary to thy holy and righteous Laws, both in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what thou haſt forbidden us, and the leaving undone what thou haſt commanded us; we have followed after and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled our own Luſts, and yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them a vile and ſlaviſh ſubjection, as to our Lords and Lawgivers, whilſt we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and been weary of thy Service, as a ſlavery, which is perfect freedom.</p>
            <p>We have forgotten thee, our God, and turning aſide to ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vanities, have ſinned againſt<pb n="126" facs="tcp:95531:70"/>thee in every ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our lives; in our health we have ſeldom thought how ſoon we might be caſt upon a ſick Bed, and in our ſickneſs have been unprepared for death, that might have been the iſſue of it; in our proſperity we have been ſecure and ſenſual, wanton, proud and unthankful, and in our adverſity we have repined and murmured with impatience and diſcontentment, and when our folly hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted our ways, our hearts
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 19. 3.</note> have fretted againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>We have ſuffered our ſelves to be prevailed upon by the pleaſures and profits of this Life, thoſe deceitful baits of the Fleſh, that having for a while gratified our ſenſual inclination, have left the ſharp and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<pb n="127" facs="tcp:95531:70"/>hook of fear and diſquiet in our conſciences: And though thou haſt graciouſly forewarn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, that our moſt pleaſant Luſts will be bitterneſs in the latter end, and the wages of Sin
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23.</note> is nothing leſs then death, and eternal miſery, yet by our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief and carnal affections, and the preſent ſeeming advantages of Sin, we have been drawn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sin; and not frighted from it by its future miſchiefs and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt ſent thy Son into the World to redeem and ſave us from our Sins, to make known thy Will, and publiſh to us his holy and good Laws, that we ſhould govern our thoughts, our words and actions by them; but we have by our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, vilely caſt away his<pb n="128" facs="tcp:95531:71"/>Scepter, and diſown'd the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of his Laws; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our profeſſions to
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 16.</note> know and believe him, we have by wicked works denyed him, and naming the Name of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19.</note> we have not departed from Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
            <p>We have ſo reſiſted and grieved thy holy Spirit, who hath earneſtly pleaded with us to caſt off our Sins, and return to our Duty, that he might in diſpleaſure withdraw from us, and forbearing his bleſſed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and leaving us deſtitute of his gracious aſſiſtance, might give us up to the blindneſs of our own minds, the unbelief and impenitent hardneſs of our hearts, and ſuffer us to go on in our own ways, till our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition were wholly hopeleſs, and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:95531:71"/>without poſſibility of recovery, we had ſinn'd our ſelves into eternal miſery.</p>
            <p>Awaken, O Lord, we pray thee, our ſleepy Conſciences, and ſo throughly convince us of the great evil of Sin, and thoſe fearful puniſhments that follow it, that we may in good earneſt and without the leaſt delay, flee from it, by a moſt ſerious and hearty repentance; and return unto the Lord our God, from
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. 1.</note> whom we have fallen, and gone aſtray by our Iniquities.</p>
            <p>Through the ſufferings and precious death of thy Son, be reconciled and ſpeak peace to us, though our offences are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry foul and heinous, and our beſt righteouſneſs cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us to look up with confidence to thine offended<pb n="130" facs="tcp:95531:72"/>Majeſty, yet in the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our bleſſed Mediator, we both pray and hope to be forgiven, being by thy ſelf aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that thou haſt given him a great and all-ſufficient Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the Atonement of great Tranſgreſſors, and exalted him
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 31.</note> to be a Prince and a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, to give repentance and remiſſion of Sins. For our ſakes, and in our ſtead, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the puniſhments that himſelf had not deſerved, he
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 5.</note> was wounded for our Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, O let us through his Stripes be healed.</p>
            <p>Help us, being delivered from wrath and condemnation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 22. 37, 39.</note> to love thee the Lord our God, with all our heart, and our<pb n="131" facs="tcp:95531:72"/>Neighbour as our ſelves, and let's evidence our love to thee by keeping thy Commandments,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 3.</note> and our love to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by forbearing and forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reproving and admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, counſelling, comforting and relieving him, and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all acts of charity and kindneſs to him.</p>
            <p>Let us herein exerciſe our
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 16.</note> ſelves to have always a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence void of offence toward thee, and toward men: enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our underſtandings with the knowledge of thy Will, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame our affections with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful love of it, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our wills unto thine, that we may readily do what thou wouldſt have us do, and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſuffer what thou wouldſt have us ſuffer. Give us that
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 3. 17.</note> 
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:95531:73"/>wiſdom which is from above, that is firſt pure, to fit us for the happineſs of another life, and then peaceable, to give a reliſh to the injoyments of this: and let us ſo imploy our ſelves in the affairs and buſineſſes of this World, as to make Religion our great buſineſs, and preſent
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1.</note> our Bodies and Souls a living Sacrifice, holy, acceptable unto thee, which is our reaſonable Service.</p>
            <p>Help us to ſubdue our inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate deſires, and all ſinful paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and when at any time we are tempted to the breach of thy Laws, with courage to reſiſt the temptation, not daring to ſin againſt thee our gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and righteous Judge; and whatever Talents thou intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to our management, health,<pb n="133" facs="tcp:95531:73"/>ſtrength or credit, our time, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, the ſeaſons of Grace, and opportunities of doing good, let us husband and improve them with that wiſdom and faithfulneſs that become them, that muſt ere long give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Stewardſhip.</p>
            <p>And becauſe through the weakneſs of our mortal nature, we can do no good thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee, grant us the help of thy Grace, that in keeping thy Commandments, we may pleaſe thee both in will and deed, and in our ſeveral Callings, whether they be publick or private; our ſeveral Conditions, whether of proſperity or adverſity; our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Relations, whether of Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands or Wives, Parents or Children, Maſters or Servants, Neighbours and Friends, we<pb n="134" facs="tcp:95531:74"/>may perform the Duties that thoſe Callings, Conditions and Relations require of us: And
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 16</note> let our light ſo ſhine before Men, that they ſeeing our good Works, may glorifie thee, our Father which art in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Whileſt we are in the way let us quickly agree with our
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 25.</note> Adverſary, and give diligence that by a ſincere repentance, and an upright univerſal obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence we may be found of thee in peace, and prepared to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt, when he ſhall ſit upon the Throne of his Glory, and weighing our thoughts, words and actions, in impartial Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances, ſhall render to us accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our works: and let the conſideration of that account leave ſuch awful impreſſions in<pb n="135" facs="tcp:95531:74"/>our hearts, as both to hinder the doing of whatever may make the thoughts of it terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to us, and cauſe us to wait for our Lord with our Loyns
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 35.</note> girt, and our Lamps burning, that at his return we may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with him into everlaſting habitations.</p>
            <p>Let thy merciful hands be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened toward all the Sons of Men, whom thy hands have made; and with a more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial kindneſs be gracious and favourable to <hi>Sion;</hi> keep thy Church and Houſhold, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in thy true Religion, and leaning upon the hope of thy heavenly Grace, let them ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more be defended by thy migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Power.</p>
            <p>Bleſs this ſinful and unworthy Nation; pardon all our Sins
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:95531:75"/>that cry aloud in thine Ears for vengeance, purely purge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 25.</note> our droſs, and take away all our Tin; deliver us from the deſtructions we have deſerved, and perpetuate thy Goſpel and true Religion among us, from generation to generation.</p>
            <p>Let the Life and Health, the peace, honour and ſafety of our Soveraign Lord, be precious in thy ſight, and let all that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern under Him in Church and State, maintain and encourage Truth and Peace, Religion, Righteouſneſs and all goodneſs: and grant that all under their Authority may lead quiet and
<note place="margin"> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 2.</note> peaceable lives in all godlineſs and honeſty.</p>
            <p>Succour and relieve all in any ſuffering condition, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence the kindneſſes of our<pb n="137" facs="tcp:95531:75"/>Friends and Benefactors ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold into their Boſom; forgive and help us heartily to forgive all that may have offered inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and unkindneſs to us.</p>
            <p>Look down upon us in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that are here lifting up our hands and hearts to thee; we bleſs thee for the peace, ſafety and refreſhment of the laſt night, beſeeching thee, ſo to guard us through the hazards, and guide us through the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of this day, that we may glorifie thee, grow in Grace, and go forward in the way that leads to everlaſting Life and happineſs, through our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, according to whoſe direction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and command we further pray;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:95531:76"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:95531:76"/>
            <head>Thurſday Evening.</head>
            <p>ALmighty and everlaſting God, the wiſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Governour of all things in Heaven and Earth, who doſt whatſoever thou pleaſeſt, and whatever thou doſt is well and wiſely done, becauſe thou doſt it: we thine unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whom thy hands have made, and ever ſince ſupported and ſupplyed, beſeech thee in mercy to look down upon us, that in a ſenſe of our own vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are here humbling our ſelves at thy Foot-ſtool acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging it thy mercy and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, that we are intruſted with one opportunity more, to implore thy pardon and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:95531:77"/>Thou might'ſt have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, the polluted Off-ſpring of diſobedient Parents, as ſoon as ever we came into the world, and ever ſince we were capable of breaking thy Laws, we have added ſin unto ſin, and heapt tranſgreſſion upon tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>We have trifled away that time, that thou haſt allotted us to make proviſion for an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Eternity, in the purſuit of pleaſure and profit, tranſient and momentany vanities, and have waged and maintained War againſt thee in thoſe ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Grace, thou haſt afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us for the making our peace: thy patience and long-ſuffering that ſhould have led us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, we have perverted to fleſhly purpoſes, and a more
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:95531:77"/>preſumptuous and impenitent progreſs in Sin.</p>
            <p>We have over-cared for, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-loved, over-deſired and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-delighted in the good things of this World, and inordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly placed our affections upon earthly and temporary injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which thou haſt fitted to ſuch things as have in them an heavenly, ſpiritual and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting excellency: How grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly and how juſtly might'ſt thou plague us with the deſires of our own hearts, and puniſh us by giving us our portion in this Life?</p>
            <p>As thou haſt multiplied thy Bleſſings we have multiplied our Inquities, and tranſgreſſed thoſe holy and good Laws which thou haſt given us as the rule of our carriage towards<pb n="142" facs="tcp:95531:78"/>thee, our ſelves and others, and wherein thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us nothing but what tends to the perfection of our nature, and the promoting of our happineſs.</p>
            <p>We have little regarded thy deſign in ſending us into this World, which was that we ſhould ſerve and pleaſe, obey and honour thee, our great Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and gracious Benefactor, and as little laid to heart the ſtrict account that we muſt ſhortly render of all our ways and works, before thy exact and impartial Tribunal, when we ſhall go hence and be here no more.</p>
            <p>We have turn'd a deaf ear to thy counſels, quencht the motions of thy Spirit, miſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved thy mercies to make<pb n="143" facs="tcp:95531:78"/>them the materials of pride, and a wanton ſenſuality, reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the tenders of thy Grace, and hardned our hearts under the correction of thy Rod; And if thou, Lord, ſhouldſt mark our Iniquities, who of us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. 3.</note> O Lord, could ſtand?</p>
            <p>How juſtly mightſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of all the bleſſings that we have forfeited? And make us feel the ſmart and ſeverity of that vengeance that thou haſt threatned? Thou mightſt inflict pains and diſeaſes in our Bodies, and purſue us with ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and the fearful foretaſts of wrath in our conſciences; thou mightſt remove thy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which we have abuſed, and withdraw thy Spirit whom we have grieved; thou mightſt give us up to the luſts of our<pb n="144" facs="tcp:95531:79"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 81. 12.</note> own hearts, that we ſhould walk in our own counſels, till we had filled up the meaſure of our Sins, and ripened our ſelves to be cut down for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting puniſhment.</p>
            <p>But with thee there is mercy
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. 4.</note> and forgiveneſs that thou mayſt be feared, and we may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned: work in us we beſeech thee, that deep contrition and through repentance, which wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ever it is wrought, is fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by forgiveneſs, and through faith in the blood of thy dear Son, who hath made peace by the blood of his Croſs; let us be juſtified and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and rejoyce in thee, having
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 11.</note> received the Atonement.</p>
            <p>Sanctifie us in Soul, Spirit and Body to thy Service, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten our minds with the<pb n="145" facs="tcp:95531:79"/>knowledge of thy Will, incline our wills to the obedience of it, purifie our affections to a love and delight in it, purge our conſciences from dead
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 14.</note> works to ſerve thee the living God, and as we have yielded our Members Servants of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs unto Iniquity, let us yield them the Servants of
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 19.</note> Righteouſneſs unto Holineſs.</p>
            <p>And becauſe we are in this World beſet with many Snares and Temptations; let us be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 8.</note> and vigilant, and walk cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 15.</note> not as Fools but as Wiſe, ſhunning all appearance of evil, and avoiding whatever may be an occaſion to the Fleſh, ſuffer us not at any time ſo to be led into temptation, as that the ſollicitations of Satan, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of this vain World,<pb n="146" facs="tcp:95531:80"/>or the ſuggeſtions of our own carnal and treacherous hearts, ſhould draw us into thoſe ſinful ways that are diſpleaſing to thee, and deſtructive to our Souls, but being alway ſenſible of how great importance and neceſſity it is, to work out our
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 12.</note> Salvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, how ſhort a time is allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us: How many and powerful Enemies are combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to hinder us: How glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous the Reward is that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed: And how dreadful and inſupportable the puniſhment that is threatned, Let us make haſt to eſcape the wrath to come, and with all our might endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to lay hold of eternal Life, preſſing toward the mark for
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 14.</note> the prize of the high Calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p> 
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:95531:80"/>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.
17.</note> And ſeeing we call on the Father, who without reſpect of perſons, judges according to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans work, let us paſs the time of our ſojourning here in fear, and never allow our ſelves the commiſſions of any known Sin, nor the omiſſion or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of any known Duty.</p>
            <p>Enable us by thy holy Spirit to ſubdue and govern our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly paſſions, to reſiſt and cruſh the firſt motions of Sin in our earthly members, faithfully to trade the ſeveral Talents thou putſt into our hands, regularly to fill up all the relations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou haſt placed us, patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bear all our burdens, cheerfully to injoy all our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and thankfully to return them to thee in thy ſervice and praiſe, and ſo wiſely to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove<pb n="148" facs="tcp:95531:81"/>all thy providences, both of bounty and ſeverity, that in our loweſt adverſity we be not dejected with anxiety and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, and in our higheſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, our hearts be not lifted up with pride to forget thee the Lord our God, but in all things the glory of thy great Name may be advanced, and the ſpiritual profit of our Souls, and their growth in grace may be promoted and furthered.</p>
            <p>Cheriſh and increaſe in us all ſincere, though feeble motions towards a more perfect and uniform obedience to thy Will, and having begun a good work in any of us, complete and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 6.</note> it until the day of Jeſus Chriſt: help us to love thee more entirely, to ſerve thee more diligently, to truſt in thee<pb n="149" facs="tcp:95531:81"/>more fully, to live to thee more exactly, to pleaſe thee more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly than we have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to done, that in a dying hour our Sins and Follies may not ſtrike us with horror and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, but our Souls may be filled with ſweet and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reflections upon thoſe ways that have been pleaſing to thee, that our God, &amp; our Conſciences may ſmile upon us, and ſpeak kindly to us, when all the things of this World are forſaking us, and we are paſſing into an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſtate. Uſe us, O Lord, whileſt we live, as Inſtruments of thy Glory in all holineſs, and as Veſſels of Glory, fill us when we dye, with everlaſting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Let all the Sons of Men whom thou haſt made capable
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:95531:82"/>of thy grace and favour be made partakers of it: Relieve them that are any way diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and enlighten them with the knowledge of thy Goſpel that ſit in darkneſs.</p>
            <p>Beautifie Mount <hi>Sion</hi> the joy of the whole Earth, with thy Salvation, deliver thy Church from ignorance and error, pride and hypocriſie, ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, ſchiſm, prophaneneſs, tyranny, ſuperſtition and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and let there be none to offend or oppreſs in thy Holy Mountain.</p>
            <p>Be gracious and merciful to this ſinful and divided Nation, though our Sins be as ſcarlet, let them be white as Snow, though
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1. 18.</note> they be red like crimſon, let them be as Wool: Eſtabliſh thy Religion in the truth and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:95531:82"/>purity of it, and let it be made beautiful by the religious lives and practices of them that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it.</p>
            <p>Let the King joy in thy
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21. 1.</note> ſtrength, O Lord, and exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejoyce in thy Salvation, bleſs him with length of days and ſafety from dangers, direct him by wiſe Counſels to juſt, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and ſucceſsful Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes; let all ſubordinate Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority be exerciſed to the beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of Vice, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of Religion and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and diſpoſe all that are under Authority to a pious obedience unto thee, a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſubjection to them that thou haſt ſet over them, not only for wrath, but for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 5.</note> ſake, and to mutual kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and a brotherly love of one another.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:95531:83"/>We come unto thee, holy Father, for a bleſſing upon our ſelves, beſeeching thee to take our Bodies and Souls, our Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Poſſeſſions, into the ſafe cuſtody of thy watchful Providence, that no evil befal
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. 10.</note> us, nor any plague come nigh our dwelling, repair the decays of our frail Bodies by a quiet and refreſhing reſt, and let us lay out our ſtrength and vigour in thy ſervice, to thy praiſe and honour, and the giving up our account with joy, at the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Lord and Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, in whom, as the High Prieſt of our Profeſſion, we offer up all our Prayers and Praiſes, and through whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone we hope to be heard and accepted, when praying, we ſay;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:95531:83"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:95531:84"/>
            <head>Friday Morning.</head>
            <p>O Lord, the great and holy
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 4.</note> God, that keepeſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Mercy, to them that
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 18.</note> love thee, and art nigh to all that call upon thee in truth and ſincerity, though thou haſt thouſands of holy and bleſſed Spirits, and ten thouſand times ten thouſands dayly Miniſtring about thy Throne, and art not at all better'd by their pure and ſpotleſs Services, yet thou haſt gracious and compaſſionate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards to the Prayers of weak and ſinful Creatures, that dwell in Houſes of Clay, thou openeſt thine Eyes to take knowledge of their condition, boweſt thine Ear to hearken to their Cryes, moveſt
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:95531:84"/>thy Bowels to pity their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and ſtretcheſt forth thine hand to relieve their wants.</p>
            <p>We poor Creatures and guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Sinners are here fallen down at thy Footſtool, adoring thine infinite perfections of holineſs and wiſdom, power, truth and goodneſs, and beſeeching thee mercifully to look upon our fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and frailties, to ſupply our bodily and ſpiritual neceſſities, to lift up the light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance upon us, and turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy Face from our deſerts of vengeance, to anſwer
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which purpoſes, we have none in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 25.</note> but thee, none in Earth that our Souls can deſire in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of thee.</p>
            <p>We dare not, we confeſs, look up to Heaven with any confidence of being accepted<pb n="156" facs="tcp:95531:85"/>for our own worthineſs, as being conſcious that we have grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly offended that holy, juſt, and Almighty Majeſty that is there ſeated on the Throne of his Glory; nor are we worthy to tread upon the Earth, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the fruits and benefits of it, where we have acted our wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſes in the ſight of Heaven.</p>
            <p>We were not only conceived in Sin, and brought forth in Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, but we have conceived Sin, and brought forth Iniquity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 32. 14</note> and are riſen up in our Fathers ſtead a generation of ſinful men; to kindle and in creaſe the anger of the Lord againſt us.</p>
            <p>We have followed after our own imaginations, and fulfilled the motions of our own Wills which have been oppoſite and contrary to the declarations of<pb n="157" facs="tcp:95531:85"/>thine, though there hath been the greateſt reaſon we ſhould receive Law from thy Mouth as our Almighty Creator, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord, and merciful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
            <p>How barren and unfruitful have we been in thy Vineyard, though thou haſt cauſed the Clouds to drop down their moiſture upon us, and watered us with the plentiful ſhowers of thy Word, and the fructifying dew of thy holy Spirit, that ſhould have made us fruitful in all good works? How have we neglected the Seaſons of Grace? And when thou haſt called us to a ſpeedy and preſent repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the anſwer of our hearts hath been, we will repent to morrow, as if we could live as long as we liſted, and had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<pb n="158" facs="tcp:95531:86"/>in our ſelves to turn to thee when we liſted.</p>
            <p>We bewail, before thee, the blindneſs of our underſtandings, the ſtubbornneſs of our wills, the vanity of our thoughts, the earthlineſs of our affections, we have hated what thou loveſt, and loved what thou hateſt, and the good things which thou haſt allowed us to love mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, and in ſubordination to thee, we have followed with eager and unbounded appetites, and embraced with our higheſt and beſt love: we have not carryed our ſelves as it becomes thoſe that are Strangers and Pilgrims upon the Earth, and profeſs to ſeek a better heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Countrey, but lived as if we were at home, and expected nothing better than what is
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:95531:86"/>to be here injoyed, as if the happineſs of this Life would never end, and that of the next would never begin.</p>
            <p>O Lord, be merciful to us, and in the multitude of thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies be reconciled to us through thy Son, and blot out all our Iniquities: give us hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to repent of all our forepaſt Sins and Follies, and ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, as
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 6.</note> to walk in him: And whatever thou denyeſt us, grant us a full pardon through our dear and all-ſufficient Redeemer, whom thou haſt ſet forth to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 25.</note> through Faith in his Blood.</p>
            <p>And let the time paſt of our
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 3.</note> Lives ſuffice to have wrought the wills of the fleſh, judging that Chriſt dyed for us, that we<pb n="160" facs="tcp:95531:87"/>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 15.</note> ſhould not henceforth live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelves, but unto him which dyed for us, and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 10.</note> help us to walk worthy of thee unto all pleaſing, being fruitful in every good work, and increaſing in the knowledge of God; give us we pray thee a
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111. 10</note> good underſtanding, not only to know, but to do thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and by growing
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18.</note> in Grace, let us increaſe the knowledge of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 8.</note> Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are pure, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report, if there be any virtue, and if there be any praiſe, let us think on, and follow theſe things, and<pb n="161" facs="tcp:95531:87"/>never be ſlothful in the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matters of thine honour, and the everlaſting intereſt and happineſs of our Souls, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently follow thoſe that have been followers of thee, and have
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 12.</note> through faith and patience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited the promiſes.</p>
            <p>And becauſe we are weak in our ſelves, and inſufficient to perform our duty, to ſubdue our luſts, to improve our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, or bear our burdens, to reſiſt and conquer our ſpiritual enemies, to ſtand our ground in the fight, or recover our ſelves from our falls, let thy grace and holy ſpirit ſtrengthen
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 16.</note> us with might in our inward man, and make us more than
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 37.</note> conquerors through him that hath loved us.</p>
            <p>Cauſe us in the firſt place to<pb n="162" facs="tcp:95531:88"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 33.</note> ſeek thy Kingdom and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and as thoſe that are
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1.</note> riſen with Chriſt, to ſeek the things that are above, not look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the things that are ſeen,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 18.</note> for they are temporal; but at the things which are not ſeen, for they are eternal: Let our

<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 20.</note> treaſure be laid up in Heaven, where Moth and Ruſt corrupt not, and where Thieves break not through, nor Steal, and let our hearts be where our trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is.</p>
            <p>Guide us continually in all the ways of wiſdom and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and defend us againſt all temptations that might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw us from them; help us to go on our way rejoycing, and working righteouſneſs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our ſeveral duties to thee and all men, with ſuch cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs<pb n="163" facs="tcp:95531:88"/>and conſtancy, as not to be weary of well-doing, but by a religious abſtinence, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate uſe of bodily refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, let our fleſh be ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued to the Spirit, that we may ever obey thy godly motions, and in a courſe of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and true holineſs run to the end of the race which thou haſt ſet before us, and be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that glorious prize which thou haſt promiſed to all them that by a patient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in well-doing ſeek for
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 7.</note> glory and honour, and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</p>
            <p>And let the proſpect and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hope of thy heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, make us upright and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, active and diligent, content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cheerful in every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of life, humble and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,<pb n="164" facs="tcp:95531:89"/>ſtedfaſt and reſolved, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denying, and heavenly minded, till thou bringeſt us to the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of thoſe inconceiveable joys, and makeſt us to drink of the Rivers of Pleaſure, that are at thy right hand for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>Do good with us, we pray thee, to the whole world, and let all that bear the image of thy power and wiſdom be made partakers of thy favour and kindneſs, let the Nations that know thee not, be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the power of darkneſs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 13.</note> and tranſlated into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of thy dear Son.</p>
            <p>Be gracious in an eſpecial manner to all whom thou haſt called to the knowledge and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of his Goſpel, forgive, gracious Father, and ſhowr<pb n="165" facs="tcp:95531:89"/>down thy bleſſings upon the inhabitants of this ſinful Land; let us prepare to meet thee by an hearty and univerſal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſo prevent thoſe judgments that ſeem to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayed, and marching forward to our deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Give Salvation to our King,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſai.</hi> 144. 10</note> and preſerve thy Servant from hidden Treacheries and the hurtful Sword; direct all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Counſels to thine honour, the promoting of true Religion, the eſtabliſhment of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Peace, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of all them that heartily love and fear thee, and let all that love thy Salvation, ſay
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 16.</note> continually, the Lord be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified.</p>
            <p>Comfort all that in any kind ſuffer adverſity, let thy holy
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:95531:90"/>Spirit refreſh them as with new Wine, whom thou haſt given Tears to drink in great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and let that good provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that hath been our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and repoſe this night, defend us from all the dangers and temptations, direct and proſper us in all the deſigns and enterpriſes of this day, and by a faithful diſcharge of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, bring us nearer to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reward of Eternal Life, which thou haſt promiſed in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, in whoſe Name and Words, we further commend our ſelves and others to thy grace and mercy, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:95531:90"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:95531:91"/>
            <head>Friday Evening.</head>
            <p>MOſt bleſſed Lord God, the Father of Mercies, our hope and preſent help, our ſtrength and our Salvation, the over-flowing and inexhauſtible Fountain of all Good, we thy poor Servants, in an humble and thankful ſenſe of thy great goodneſs, and emboldned by the invitation of thy gracious promiſes, preſent our ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne of thy Grace, to offer up our ſupplications, and thankſgivings through the Mediation of thy dear Son, in whom thou haſt given us acceſs
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 12.</note> with confidence, through the Faith of him.</p>
            <p>We are moſt unworthy in<pb n="169" facs="tcp:95531:91"/>our ſelves to receive bleſſings, or offer praiſes, but worthy art thou, O Lord, to receive ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory, and bleſſing, and thankſgiving, as for thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine perfections which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend, ſo for thine abundant kindneſſes towards us, which we can neither deſerve nor number.</p>
            <p>Thou didſt frame and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us in the Womb, by thy wiſdom and power, and haſt maintained and provided for us by thy goodneſs and bounty, ever ſince thou haſt brought us into life and being; giving us richly all things to injoy, not only the neceſſaries, but conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of Life, whereby it hath been made eaſie and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to us.</p>
            <p>But above all from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom<pb n="170" facs="tcp:95531:92"/>of our hearts we praiſe, a dore and magnifie thy tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent wiſdom &amp; ſuperlative love in that ineſtimable benefit of our Redemption, by the bitter ſufferings and bloody Death of thy dear Son, that when we had loſt and undone our ſelves, were lyable to wrath and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal miſery, when we lay wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in our own blood, and there was no Eye to pity, no Hand to relieve us, thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemedſt us in ſuch a way as no creature had wiſdom to contrive, worthineſs to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, or power to effect.</p>
            <p>We praiſe thee O Lord, that thou haſt in thy Goſpel mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted this great and admirable Salvation, made thy goodneſs to paſs before us, and fully and plainly inſtructed us in our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:95531:92"/>that in performing the one we might be made partakers of the other; that thou haſt afforded us the means of Grace, thy Word and Sacraments, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of thy publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the motions and aſſiſtances of thy holy Spirit, that thou haſt quickned our obedience by the hopes of a glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence.</p>
            <p>Give us, we pray thee, a due ſenſe of all thy mercies, and withdraw not thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from us; if our worthineſs had been to procure theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, they had never been put into our hands and if any thing but thy goodneſs were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue them, we could never hold them; our own wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs might correct us, and our
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 19.</note> back-ſlidings reprove us, for we<pb n="172" facs="tcp:95531:93"/>have ſinned and done very foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly.</p>
            <p>We have perverted and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted our ways, and profeſſing
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 16.</note> to know thee, have in our works denyed thee, we have called thee our Father, but have not loved and honoured thee, as Children, our Maſter, but have not feared and obeyed thee as Servants, our Friend and Benefactor, but have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed our enmity againſt thee in wicked works; we have
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19.</note> named the Name of Chriſt, but not departed from Iniquity, vowed allegiance to thee in our Baptiſm, but have broken thy Bonds aſunder, and caſt away thy Cords from us, and as if the temptations of the World and the Devil would not have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough prevailed to defile and<pb n="173" facs="tcp:95531:93"/>deſtroy us, we have tempted our ſelves, and been drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of our own luſt and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticed.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 14.</note> 
            </p>
            <p>We have not had that ſenſe of thy Love, as to love thee with all our hearts; that ſenſe of thy Mercies, as with thoſe Cords of kindneſs to be drawn to thy Service; that ſenſe of thy diſpleaſure, as to fear offending thee; that ſenſe of Sins filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and deformity, as to hate and flee from it with our whole Souls; nor have we had that belief of Heavens Glory and Happineſs, as by a fruitfulneſs in good works to preſs toward it with all our might; that active and vigorous diligence that ſhould have been uſed to promote the ſpiritual good of our Souls, and ſecure their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal<pb n="174" facs="tcp:95531:94"/>intereſt, we have with great folly miſimployed in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing the pleaſures and profits of this World, and in aſſuring thoſe fickle and ſlippery vanities, that are not capable of a long, or certain continuance.</p>
            <p>O Lord have mercy upon us, miſerable offenders, and help us ſo to repent of all the Sins we have committed, as never more to commit the Sins of which we have repented, and work in us a true and a lively faith in thy dear Son, our bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, who is both God and Man, that God and Man may be reconciled, and through the blood of his Croſs, grant us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and remiſſion of Sins, and by that precious Blood, ſprinkled upon our Conſciences,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 14.</note> purge them from dead Works,<pb n="175" facs="tcp:95531:94"/>to ſerve thee the living God.</p>
            <p>Waſh our hearts from wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 14.</note> that we may be ſaved, and let not vain thoughts lodg within us, help us ſo to govern our Tongue, that unruly Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that no corrupt communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation may at any time proceed out of our Mouth, but that
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 29.</note> which is good to the uſe of edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, that it may miniſter grace unto the hearers: and let all our actions be directed by thy Word, and deſigned to thy Glory.</p>
            <p>That delight and ſatisfaction that we might vainly, and to no purpoſe ſeek, in ſenſual plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and the impure gratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Fleſh, let us ſeek and find in the ways of holineſs, and a dutiful compliance with thy Will, that in loving and keeping<pb n="176" facs="tcp:95531:95"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 165.</note> thy Law, we may have great peace, and nothing may offend us: and in the midſt of all the troubles and confuſions of the World, we may rejoyce in our reconciliation with thee, and in the harmony and peaceful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of our own conſciences.</p>
            <p>Bleſs us in our Callings and Imployments, that we may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 30. 8. 9.</note> abound in Riches, leſt we be full and deny thee, nor be pinched with extream want, leſt we be tempted to the evils that attend an impoveriſhed State, but in thy wiſe and good providence, carve out to us ſuch a convenient ſhare of worldly good things, health and ſtrength, riches and reputation, that we may faithfully ſerve thee, and be cheerfully helpful to our brethren. Let thy love
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:95531:95"/>and holy fear ſo intermix with and ſweeten all our earthly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, that we may eat our
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9. 7.</note> Bread with joy, and drink our Wine with a merry heart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou accepteſt our works.</p>
            <p>In every condition of Life be thou our Guide, and our Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, help us to love and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in thee above our higheſt and beſt comforts, and under our croſſes, with patience and cheerfulneſs to reſign up our ſelves to thy wiſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous providence, and with a ſtedfaſt faith to rely upon thy gracious and faithful promiſes. Let our converſation be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5.</note> covetouſneſs, and make us content with ſuch things as we have, becauſe thou haſt ſaid, thou wilt never leave us, nor forſake us: by all the changes
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:95531:96"/>we meet with in this World, prepare us, O Lord, for our laſt and great change, when we ſhall leave it; that death our laſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy may be to us neither dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous nor dreadful, but a ſweet and deſireable paſſage to a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and glorious immortality.</p>
            <p>And in theſe our Prayers we commend (allied by a common Brotherhood) all Mankind to thy Grace and Favour, heal the Sick, eaſe the pained, relieve the Oppreſſed, ſupply the Impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, feed the Hungry, cloath the Naked, comfort the Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, cauſe them that are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted in Conſcience to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, ſpread forth the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy Son into all the dark corners of the World, that
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49. 6.</note> he may be thy Light and thy Salvation unto the end of the Earth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:95531:96"/>Let thy continual pity cleanſe and defend thy Church, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot continue in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty without thy ſuccour, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it evermore by thy help, and goodneſs.</p>
            <p>O be gracious and favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Land of our Nativity, forgive all our crying Sins, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert thy threatned and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Judgments, cleanſe our defilements, heal our divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſtabliſh us in truth, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and peace, perpetuate thy Goſpel and Ordinances, the pledges of thy love and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and grant that we may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way walk worthy of thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable benefits.</p>
            <p>Bleſs, preſerve, direct and proſper our Sovereign Lord the King, in all his thoughts, words and works, let him ever ſeek thy
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:95531:97"/>honour and glory, and ſtudy to preſerve thy People committed to his charge, in wealth, peace and godlineſs. Let the Biſhops and Paſtors of thy Church by their heavenly Doctrine and exemplary Lives, their diligent labours, vigilant care, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent carriage, adorn the Goſpel, ſilence gainſayers, and win ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to righteouſneſs: and let Magiſtrates by an equal and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different adminiſtration of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, uphold Religion and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and ſuppreſs Vice and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs; and grant that all under Authority may follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Peace and Holineſs, obeying thoſe that are over them for conſcience ſake, loving and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing one another, leading quiet and peaceable Lives in all godlineſs and honeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:95531:97"/>Follow us with thy mercy and loving kindneſs this night, and let thy good providence, that neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps, defend and protect us, that no danger or diſturbance in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion of our own thoughts, care and reaſon, harm or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy us: And ſo repair our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying ſpirits by a quiet and peaceful reſt, that we may ſerve thee with healthful bodies and cheerful minds, the next day, and all our days, till thou bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt us to that bleſſed ſtate where eating, and drinking, and ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall be no more, but we ſhall be eternally happy in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and injoying thee through thy dear Son, our ever bleſſed Redeemer, through whoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits alone we hope to be heard, and in whoſe words we further pray;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:95531:98"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="183" facs="tcp:95531:98"/>
            <head>Saturday Morning.</head>
            <p>O Eternal Lord God, the great Creator and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of Heaven and of Earth, and our moſt merciful Father in Chriſt Jeſus, Look down, we beſeech thee, from Heaven, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us vile Duſt and Aſhes, and grant that when we call upon thee with our Lips, our Hearts may not be far from thee.</p>
            <p>We do humbly acknowledge the great ſinfulneſs and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Natures; the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Minds, the perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Wills, the diſorder and depravedneſs of our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the vanity of our thoughts. We acknowledge that we are by nature the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:95531:99"/>of Wrath, and that there is no ſound or clean part in us.</p>
            <p>We do farther confeſs, that we have by many actual ſins made our ſelves more the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath than we were by Nature. We confeſs our ſins of omiſſion as well as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, our ſins againſt Thee, our Brother and our own Souls. We have many ways offended thee in thought, word and deed: And if thou ſhouldſt mark Iniquities, we were not able to ſtand before thee.</p>
            <p>We have ſinned againſt light and knowledge, after the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of thy Mercies, under ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient means of Grace, after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſolemn Vows of better obedience. We have not been awakened out of our ſinful and<pb n="185" facs="tcp:95531:99"/>careleſs Life by the greateſt of thy Judgments; but have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after the convictions of our own Conſciences, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the evil of depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from thee, after many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions and many repetitions. We have grieved thy Spirit, defaced thy Image, miſpent our precious time, trifled in the great concernments of Eternity, and in great meaſure received the grace of thee our God in vain. We humble our ſelves before thee, O God, and deſire to be vile in our own Eyes, as we have made our ſelves ſo in thine. Enter not into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thy Servants, O Lord, for no Fleſh ſhall be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in thy ſight.</p>
            <p>Have mercy upon us, O Lord, have mercy upon us for
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:95531:100"/>Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, who is the Propitiation for our Sins, and ever lives to make interceſſion for thoſe who come unto God by him.</p>
            <p>Grant that he may not be an empty Name and Title to us, but that he may bleſs us in turning us from our Iniquities, and may give us Repentance as well as forgiveneſs of Sins.</p>
            <p>And we moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to give us thy holy Spirit; puriſie and cleanſe our Hearts, and help us that we may fear, love and deſire thee above all things. Make us like unto thee, and help us that we may chearfully do and ſuffer thy whole Will. Supply all our wants, ſanctifie all thy dealings to us, direct us in our difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and enable us againſt our Sins.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:95531:100"/>Deliver us, O Lord, from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very evil thing, from hardneſs of Heart, and contempt of thy Word: keep us from being tempted above what we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and enable us by thy Grace againſt the aſſaults of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the Temptations of the World and the Fleſh, and make us at the laſt partakers of Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life.</p>
            <p>Be merciful, we pray thee, to the whole World: enlarge the Kingdom of Chriſt, and let the whole World be filled with the knowledge of thee, and of thy Son, as the Waters cover the Sea.</p>
            <p>Bleſs thy whole Church: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form whatever is amiſs in the belief or lives of Chriſtians: Grant that all who name the Name of Chriſt may depart from all Iniquity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:95531:101"/>Be gracious to theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. Pardon our Sins, pity our Diſtractions, heal our Breaches, unite us to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, reconcile us all to thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, and defend us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Enemies.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially we pray thee to bleſs the King: endue his Heart with all the Graces of thy holy Spirit, defend Him againſt all His Enemies; bleſs Him in His Royal Relations, and teach His Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Bleſs all the Governours and Inſtructors of thy Church, and grant they may all in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places anſwer the end of their Inſtitution and Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Pity all that are afflicted. Comfort them that mourn, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the Sick and Weak, have<pb n="189" facs="tcp:95531:101"/>compaſſion on them who lye a dying, and take them not out of this Life before they are fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a better Life than this.</p>
            <p>Bleſs all our Friends with all the Bleſſings of this and of a better Life. Forgive our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, convert and turn their hearts.</p>
            <p>We bleſs thee for all thy Mercies to us, both of this and a better Life: above all we bleſs thee for Jeſus Chriſt, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeeching thee, ſo to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect our hearts with the ſenſe of thy Mercies, that thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may lead us to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: And all we beg for Chriſt his ſake, who hath taught us, when we pray, to ſay;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:95531:102"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="191" facs="tcp:95531:102"/>
            <head>Saturday Evening.</head>
            <p>MOſt gracious and ever bleſſed Lord God, and our moſt merciful Father in Chriſt Jeſus, we that are leſs than the leaſt of thy mercies, deſire in all humility to come into thy preſence, and beſeech thee for Chriſt's ſake, to have a regard unto us.</p>
            <p>We do acknowledge before thee, our loſt and undone con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition without thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy towards us: we have grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly offended thee in thought, word and deed: been unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for thy Mercies, incorrigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble under thy Judgments, and very unprofitable under the means of Grace. We humble
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:95531:103"/>our ſelves before thee for the Sins of our whole Life; and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly for the Sins of this day, with all the circumſtances of aggravation, with which they have been attended.</p>
            <p>Pardon us, O Lord, we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray thee, for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt who came into the World, to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt. Give us a true faith in him, and work in us a ſincere and hearty repentance never to be repented of. And, we pray thee, aſſiſt us by thy Grace, that we may for the time to come, walk before thee in newneſs of Life.</p>
            <p>Enlighten our Minds, rectifie our Wills, ſanctifie our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and purifie all the thoughts &amp; intentions of our Hearts. Make us fit Temples for thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit<pb n="193" facs="tcp:95531:103"/>to dwell in, and grant that he who is in us may be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than he who is in the World.</p>
            <p>Be with us under all our Tryals and Temptations, and prepare us for all events of things. Sanctifie all thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations to us, and give us Wiſdom and a ſaving Knowledge of thee and of thy Son. Make us humble and lowly, heavenly minded and pure in heart, patient un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der every trouble, contented in every condition, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to thy holy and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Will.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the way of Man is not in himſelf, we humbly pray thee to direct and guide us in the way that we ſhould go. Take care of our Affairs, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper<pb n="194" facs="tcp:95531:104"/>all our Undertakings which are agreeable to thy heavenly Will; help us that we may live Righteouſly, So berly and Godly in this preſent World.</p>
            <p>Caſt out of our mind every thing that is diſpleaſing to thee: diſcharge our Hearts of all Pride, Ambition, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Malice, Vain Conceit of our Selves. And grant that we may not be overcome by the Temptations of the Devil, the World and the Fleſh: And that we may not go out of this World with falſe hopes and expectations about us.</p>
            <p>Prepare us, we pray thee, for our latter end. When our Heart and Fleſh ſhall fail us, be thou the ſtrength of our Heart
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:95531:104"/>and our Portion for ever: And ſuffer us not at our laſt hour for any Pains or Agonies of Death to fall away from thee: make us willing and ready to leave this World, whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe thee to call us hence.</p>
            <p>Be merciful to the whole race of Mankind: Advance the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt in the World; Let the People praiſe thee, O God, let all the People praiſe thee. Eſpecially be merciful to thy whole Church; Bleſs theſe Kingdoms, and ſettle us upon the Foundations of Righteouſneſs, of Truth and Peace.</p>
            <p>Bleſs with the choiceſt of thy Bleſſings, our Sovereign Lord the King. Protect His Royal Perſon, bleſs His Government,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:95531:105"/>let His days be many and His Reign proſperous. And bleſs His Royal Relations, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed His Counſellors, and all in Authority under Him, and grant that under Him we may live quiet and peaceable Lives, in all godlineſs and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.</p>
            <p>Bleſs all that miniſter in holy things, and grant they may gain many unto Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Have compaſſion upon the Afflicted, upon the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and the Poor, upon Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and Fatherleſs, upon all that are perſecuted for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake, upon the Sick and the Weak, upon all that are troubled in mind, and at the point of Death: Be merciful to them all accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:95531:105"/>to their ſeveral neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>We beſeech thee to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to our Friends and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give all our Enemies.</p>
            <p>We bleſs thy holy Name for all thy mercies to us and to all the World; for thy preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of us this day, for the means of Grace and the hope of Glory. We bleſs thee above all for Jeſus Chriſt, we praiſe thee for the clear revelation of thy Will the Promiſe of thy Spirit, the time and ſpace of Repentance which thou art pleaſed to continue to us; for any meaſure of Health and Strength, the many Mercies which we injoy, and which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers want, and which we have been unthankful for. Write a Law of thankfulneſs upon our<pb n="198" facs="tcp:95531:106"/>Hearts, we humbly pray thee, and grant that we may be bettered by all thy Mercies. Take us, we pray thee, into thy protection this night, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie and prepare our Hearts for all the ſolemn Duties and Services of the next Day, and grant all our Requeſts for Chriſt's ſake, in whoſe words we further call upon thee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:95531:106"/>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy Will be done in Earth, As it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread. And forgive us our Treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that Treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, And the Glory, For ever and ever.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
